<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To en archy: or, An exercitation upon a momentous question in divinity, and case of conscience viz. whether it be lawfull for any person to act contrary to the opinion of his own consicence, formed from arguments that to him appear very probable, though not necessary or demonstrative. Where the opinions of the papists, Vasquez, Sanches, Azonius, &amp;c. are shewed, as also the opinions of some Protestants, viz. Mr. Hooker, Bp Sanderson, Dr. Fulwood, &amp;c. and compared with the opinions of others; the negative part of the question maintained; the unreasonableness of the popish opinions, and some Protestants, for blind obedience, detected; and many other things discoursed. By a Protestant.</title>
            <author>Protestant.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39389</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5314_CANCELLED</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214929</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826972</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826972</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109403</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39389)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109403)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1698:58, 1845:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To en archy: or, An exercitation upon a momentous question in divinity, and case of conscience viz. whether it be lawfull for any person to act contrary to the opinion of his own consicence, formed from arguments that to him appear very probable, though not necessary or demonstrative. Where the opinions of the papists, Vasquez, Sanches, Azonius, &amp;c. are shewed, as also the opinions of some Protestants, viz. Mr. Hooker, Bp Sanderson, Dr. Fulwood, &amp;c. and compared with the opinions of others; the negative part of the question maintained; the unreasonableness of the popish opinions, and some Protestants, for blind obedience, detected; and many other things discoursed. By a Protestant.</title>
                  <author>Protestant.</author>
                  <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to John Collinges.</note>
                  <note>The first three words of the title are in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Identified on reel as C5314 (entry cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the originals in: Union Theological Seminary Library; Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109403:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109403:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΤΟ 'ΕΝ 'ΑΡΧΗ: OR, An Exercitation UPON A MOMENTOUS QUESTION IN <hi>Divinity,</hi> and <hi>Caſe of Conſcience:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VIZ. <hi>Whether it be lawfull for any Perſon to Act contrary to the Opinion of his own Conſcience, formed from Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that to him appear very Probable, though not</hi> Neceſſary <hi>or</hi> Demonſtrative.</p>
            <p>WHERE The <hi>Opinions</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts, Vaſquez, Sanches, Azo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> &amp;c. are ſhewed, as alſo the <hi>Opinions</hi> of ſome <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> viz. Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> B<hi rend="sup">p</hi> 
               <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Fulwood,</hi> &amp;c. and compared with the <hi>Opinions</hi> of others; The <hi>Negative Part</hi> of the <hi>Queſtion</hi> Maintained; the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh Opinions,</hi> and <hi>ſome Proteſtants,</hi> for <hi>Blind Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> detected; and many other things diſcourſed.</p>
            <p>By a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Cum ergo Opinionem aliquam, non ob aſſenſum aliorum, ſed ob Cauſas Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles, pro verâ habes, obligatus es in Conſcientiâ ne contra eam agas, licet Superiores aliud à te exigant, donec rationes veriores audias; &amp;c. <bibl>
                  <hi>Baldvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in Caſ. Conſ. l. 1. cap. 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Quicquid fit contra Conſcientiam, peccatum eſt: Sive Conſcientia ſit Errans, ſive Opinans, ſive rectè informata. <bibl>
                  <hi>Alſted. in Theol. Caſ. c. 2. n. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Nunquam licet contra propriam Opinionem, vel certam vel probabilem agere, propter aliorum Authoritatem. <bibl>
                  <hi>Ames in Caſ. l. 1. cap. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:109403:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109403:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou canſt not but think we have been a little ſenſible of the many <hi>Attacques,</hi> have been made upon our <hi>Reputation</hi> in the ſight of the World, repreſenting us as perſons <hi>hardened with Prejudice, blinded with Paſſion, biaſſed by ſome falſe, yet plauſible Principles which we muſt not recant,</hi> Men who have nothing to ſay for our ſelves, <hi>facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſeditious, ungovernable, fit for Gallies,</hi> &amp;c. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as a late Author tells his <hi>Lord, That all the Saying and Writing in the World</hi> concerning us, <hi>will be to no purpoſe;</hi> (nor indeed will it, if it be no more <hi>nervous</hi> than any thing we ſee in his Book,) for as to his two <hi>Caſes,</hi> he firſt ſuppoſeth, <hi>That we judge the things required of us lawfull,</hi> (is not this Noble diſputing, to <hi>Begg the Queſtion?</hi>) we would fain have him name us one <hi>Non-con.</hi> of that mind: But it was not enough for him to begg it once, but in his <hi>Caſe of Scandal,</hi> he beggs again; That thoſe who urge <hi>Scandal</hi> as an Argument, underſtand by it, only <hi>Grieving or diſpleaſing ſome.</hi> Moſt ridiculous! Can he ſhew us any <hi>Non-con.</hi> that ever ſaid, <hi>That
<pb facs="tcp:109403:3"/>indeed he judged the thing Lawfull, but becauſe ſome People would be grieved or angred, therefore he would not Conform. Ad Populum phaleras.</hi> It is true, the Argument from Scandal is ſometimes uſed, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in that Sence wherein himſelf judgeth it good; <hi>That is, becauſe by our doing of it, ſuppoſing any of us do think ſome thing lawfull, yet ſhould we doe it, we ſhould be occaſion of ſin to others, probably inducing them to doe it, who judge it unlawfull.</hi> But the truth is, take the Argument in this ſence, it is not valuable, not one of us of a thouſand thinks the things required, Lawfull; for thoſe that do ſo, we ſhould adviſe them, to contemn the Scandal, becauſe of the Superiours Command. In his Second <hi>Caſe</hi> he quits himſelf as well, for he beggs again <hi>the Queſtion: That the ſuffering Nonconformiſts</hi> would grant him, <hi>that they do not judge they ſuffer in the Exerciſe of True Religion;</hi> that is ſurely, <hi>that they may not preſumptuouſly ſin againſt God.</hi> Indeed here he endeavours to prove it by a ſeries of <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> but there he pitifully beggs both his 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Concluſion,</hi> and his 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>; upon which two all the reſt hang. For though it be granted, that it belongs to the Magiſtrate, to <hi>determine Circumſtances in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, i. e.</hi> Circumſtances of Action, <hi>quatenus</hi> an <hi>humane action,</hi> whether <hi>neceſſary to it,</hi> as <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place;</hi> or <hi>convenient</hi> for it, and <hi>decent, i. e.</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly ſo, from the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> and the <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Guiſe</hi> and Cuſtom of the place: Yet the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi> never yielded any Power under Heaven, a Right to appoint <hi>Ceremonies, i. e.</hi> Circumſtances appropriated to the Action as <hi>Religious;</hi> theſe they ſay, (contrary to his third Concluſion,) are <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in Scripture,</hi> or if not, <hi>may be left to liberty,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:109403:3"/>(contrary to his fourth Concluſion.) Thus <hi>Reader,</hi> judge how fairly we are dealt with. One writes like a <hi>Bedlam,</hi> and rails like a Female out of <hi>Billings-gate,</hi> inſtead of arguing; another comes out like <hi>a man of Warr,</hi> but will not ſight, unleſs we will firſt lay down our Arms, grant him <hi>the things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> and then he will <hi>crow over us at an inſufferable rate.</hi> 'Tis time to put an end to theſe things; we have therefore thought fit, To <hi>revoke</hi> this whole Controverſie to an <hi>Original Queſtion;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether it be lawfull to act againſt an Opining Conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If our Brethren will agree with us in the <hi>Negative,</hi> we will joyn Iſſue with them there, <hi>Whether we have not probable Arguments to induce us,</hi> to <hi>conclude the things required of us, unlawfull;</hi> or at leaſt to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply what in this point is defective. For we think we need ask our liberty for no longer time than, till <hi>Cotton, Ames, Gilleſpy, Calderwood, Bradſhaw,</hi> and forty more be anſwered. If theſe Eager Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, be Men, and Scholars, let them come forth, leave railing, and miſrepreſenting our Opinions, and take them as we ſtate them, and anſwer ſtrictly. If not, Silence would tend more to their reputation amongſt all intelligent perſons, than ſuch imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Scriblings.</p>
            <p>We have been more willing to ſpeak to this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, becauſe it is the very <hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> (ſo much feared.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is lawfull for men to act contrary to the Opinions of their own Conſciences, if other Doctors think it lawfull and neceſſary, if Superiours com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Poſſeſs but people of the Brutiſhneſs of this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb facs="tcp:109403:4"/>and you have done more to barre out Popery, than confuting twenty of their particular Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are but Superſtructures upon this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. 'Tis obliging men to <hi>Believe as the Church believes,</hi> and to <hi>doe all they are commanded by Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Superiours, without diſputing with, or heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to their own Judgements,</hi> that muſt bring Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery into any Nation, ſo full of Knowledge as <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is, if ever it comes on. Other things indeed may bring in <hi>Perſecution,</hi> but not <hi>Popery;</hi> and that <hi>Perſecution</hi> will not be of many dayes. Seeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Author of the Caſes of <hi>Scandal and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> thought it worthy of him, to lay aſide his thoughts of writing againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as he tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 3. of his <hi>Introduction,</hi> to ſpeak againſt <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts,</hi> (and that when he had no more to ſay than that Book hath,) and that upon the advice of ſo grave a Perſon as B<hi rend="sup">p</hi> 
               <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> (whom we reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as better underſtanding his Learning, and candid ſtating Queſtions, and judicious ſpeaking to them.) We hope we ſhall be excuſed in our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to ſpeak to a <hi>Queſtion,</hi> which while it offers ſomething in our own defence, doth manifeſtly ſtrike at the very <hi>root and Foundation of the Popiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> which almoſt wholly owes it ſelf to <hi>Blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi> Reader, we ſhall not complement thee: Read, acquit or condemn us, as thou ſeeſt cauſe, upon weighing what we ſay, and judge what is againſt us, <hi>praeter merum imperium &amp; convitia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109403:4"/>
            <head>Whether it be lawful to act contrary to an Opining Conſcience?</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Queſtion ſhortly ſtated. The terms [Conſcience,] and [Opining] opened: The Various complexions of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; ariſing from the different mediums by which light ſhines into a ſoul about a Practical Propoſition. The terms of Faith, Science, Opinion, Doubting, Suſpition, Scruple, opened. The true notion of a Fixed Conſcience, an Opining Conſcience, a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a Scruputons Conſcience. The Schoolmens Notion of an Opinion. The Queſtion fully ſtated. The method propounded for handling it.</head>
               <p>SECT. I.</p>
               <p>THe queſtion is ſhortly and plainly this. <hi>Whether without ſinning againſt God, a man can act contrary to the dictate of his own Conſcience, though but Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> By Conſcience, not to trouble our Reader with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Notions, and <hi>Homonymies</hi> of it; which have little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to our intended diſcourſe: we mean, <hi>That Judgement in man, by which he determineth concerning good or evil, as it
<pb facs="tcp:109403:5"/>relateth to practice, according to the Dictate of Natural, or enlightened Reaſon.</hi> We think it well deſcribed by the <hi>Schoolmen, Judicium quo aliquid bonum eſſe vel malum judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Sanehes. in Op. mor. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.1. Reaſon is a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faculty in man, by which he diſcourſeth <hi>Concluſions</hi> from <hi>Principles;</hi> and theſe either <hi>Connate</hi> or <hi>Natural,</hi> or <hi>acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> from exerciſe, reading and comparing things, with things, Now the work of Reaſon is, when a <hi>practical Propoſition</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to it, to ſit as a Judge upon it, enquiring either upon the <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>falſhod</hi> of it, by comparing it with theſe Principle, hence it maketh up a <hi>Judgement</hi> whether the <hi>Propoſition</hi> be <hi>true</hi> or <hi>falſe, good</hi> or <hi>bad.</hi> This Judgment Divines call <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium ſingulare:</hi> or <hi>Judicium conſcientiae practicum,</hi> The <hi>Judgment of Conſcience,</hi> or Conſcience it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Sect. 2. This Judgment is made up by certain <hi>Mediums,</hi> or arguments, which do not in all caſes, ſhine with the like degree of light upon the ſoul: for as there is a difference in Propoſitions, ſome are <hi>True,</hi> ſome are <hi>falſe;</hi> of thoſe which are, ſome are <hi>neceſſarily</hi> ſo: So as it is impoſſible they ſhould be falſe. Some are <hi>contingently</hi> ſo, which are true, but it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they may be, or might have been falſe; as now <hi>That God is good,</hi> is a Propoſition <hi>neceſſarily true.</hi> That <hi>Peter was good</hi> is true, but no more than <hi>contingently</hi> ſo, for he was bad: So there is likewiſe a great difference in the minds aſſent to Propoſitions; ſome it <hi>agrees</hi> to, ſome it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth. Of thoſe to which it agreeth, There are ſome to which it agreeth firmly, and fixedly, without the leaſt doubt of them. Now theſe are either ſuch as are <hi>Propoſitions of faith,</hi> being things plainly revealed in the word of God: or, Matters <hi>evident to ſenſe.</hi> Thus every man will agree the <hi>fire is hot,</hi> and that the <hi>Sun ſhines at noon day:</hi> or elſe ſuch, <hi>which have a certain cauſe of their truth, which we can ſee.</hi> The Aſſent of the mind to the firſt is called <hi>Faith,</hi> which is <hi>the minds aſſent to the truth of a Propoſition, upon the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God revealing it.</hi> The Aſſent of the mind to the two latter is called <hi>Science.</hi> Now there are other Propoſitions, for which the ſoul can have no ſuch <hi>Mediums</hi> as theſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb facs="tcp:109403:5"/>them by, But <hi>either,</hi> ſome <hi>Humane Authority,</hi> or ſome <hi>probable Reaſon.</hi> The <hi>Aſſent</hi> which the mind giveth upon either of theſe accounts is called <hi>Opinion,</hi> which is but the <hi>Judgement</hi> of Conſcience, from <hi>probable Arguments,</hi> uſually called <hi>dialectick arguments,</hi> for there are not many things capable of demonſtration.</p>
               <p>§. 3. Hence the certainty of the Mind, as to the Truth, or Falſhood of any propoſition, is, 1. Either <hi>Supernatural,</hi> from Divine Revelation; or 2. <hi>Natural,</hi> from the Evidence of <hi>Senſe,</hi> or <hi>Demonſtration;</hi> or 3. <hi>Moral,</hi> from probable <hi>Authority</hi> or <hi>Arguments.</hi> But now in regard of the differing Force of Arguments, and the variety of them, for, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame propoſition: This aſſent is capable of vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous degrees, and may variouſly be incumbred. A Chriſtian may give ſome Credit to a propoſition, yet have ſome <hi>ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> about it (which like little ſtones in the ſhooe, from whence the term is borrowed) may trouble his Practice: Or may have ſome <hi>doubts</hi> whether the thing be true or no: Or I may have an <hi>Opinion,</hi> that is, verily judge the thing to be ſo, or not ſo.</p>
               <p>§. 4. The Philoſopher tells us, that in Moral things, a Moral certainty is enough to Act upon; and indeed it muſt be ſo, for as to moſt things of particular practice, we can neither be <hi>Naturally</hi> nor <hi>Supernaturally</hi> aſcertained. Not <hi>Naturally,</hi> becauſe we cannot ſee the certain Cauſes. Not <hi>Supernaturally,</hi> for it had been impoſſible that God's Word ſhould have ſet every individual Man a particular Rule for every individual Action. In theſe Caſes therefore (as we ſaid) a <hi>Moral certainty</hi> is ground enough for Action, which is, or may be conſiſtent with ſome Scruples or Fears. For Example, ſuppoſe this the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether a Man be ſit to Receive the Supper of the Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be he cannot fully ſatisfie himſelf, but he may have ſome fears, and jealouſies, and Scruples, of the Reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109403:6"/>of which, he can give himſelf no very good Account; but yet he finds ſo much ground to conclude he is, that he is Morally certain. In this caſe he is bound not to omit it. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe one ſick of a <hi>Quinſie,</hi> or <hi>Pleuriſie,</hi> or ſome other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, uſually Mortal without timely Bleeding, and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of means: He is not <hi>Mathematically,</hi> or <hi>Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively</hi> certain, that he ſhall dye, if he doth not uſe ſuch means, (his Natural ſtrength may Conquer it) but he may be <hi>Moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> certain, and ſo Obliged to Act. Whether a Man may be ſaid to know, that of which he is onely <hi>Morally certain,</hi> is a little <hi>Velitation</hi> among Critical Philoſophers. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells us, that what falleth under <hi>Science,</hi> conſidered as an Habit of the Mind, muſt be ſomething demonſtrable, but this is onely a ſtrife about words.</p>
               <p>§. 5. Much in the preſent Debate, depending upon the term <hi>Opining,</hi> the fixing of the true Notion of an <hi>Opinion,</hi> or at leaſt, ſuch a one as we underſtand in the Queſtion is of great Conſequence. It is ſometimes uſed to ſignifie a <hi>ſudden and raſh aſſent of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding to a propoſition.</hi> But in this ſence, we have nothing to do with it. 2. <hi>It is taken for the aſſent of the Mind to one part of a propoſition as true, yet not without fear of being miſtaken.</hi> 3. But Thirdly (in which ſence we uſe it) It is alſo taken to ſignifie <hi>the Souls aſſent to a propoſition upon probable Arguments.</hi> That is ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as do not demonſtrate the thing to the Soul, ſo as to put it out of all poſſibility of doubting, but make it appear very like to be true. <hi>Probabile est quod quum certum non ſit magis tamen videtur eſſe verum vel falſum,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Logician. Aquinas,</hi> in his Summs, <hi>Qu.</hi> 1. <hi>Art.</hi> 4. Deſcribes an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion according to the Second Notion, thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Act of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding, inclining to one part of a Contradiction, not without a fear of the Truth of the other part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Valentia</hi> (as he is quoted by <hi>Sanchez, Op. Mor. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9.) will allow no Man any longer to keep within the Latitude of on <hi>Opinion,</hi> than while he perſwades himſelf, that although he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109403:6"/>hath probable Reaſons to judge this, or that Lawful, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, yet they are not ſuch; but (if he could hit on it) might be Anſwered by himſelf, or ſome other: But yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sanchez,</hi> nor <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> nor <hi>Azorius</hi> will allow this ſtreightned Notion of an <hi>Opinion,</hi> though we cannot ſee how they will avoid it, till they put <hi>[cum formidine alterius]</hi> out of their own Deſcriptions, for what ſhould he who openeth be afraid of, but that his Arguments are Anſwerable? So as in effect they all agree, That a Man perſwaded upon proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Arguments, of the Lawfulneſs, or Unlawfulneſs of a th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, no longer Opineth, than he feareth his own Reaſons may be Anſwered. But to us, <hi>Be it ſo, or ſo,</hi> it is all a caſe; we call that an Opinion, which is <hi>The Aſſent of the Mind to a Propoſition upon Arguments, not Demonſtrably, but Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly certain.</hi> And we have here the Advantage; for if we prove it not Lawful to act againſt an <hi>Opining Conſcience</hi> in their ſence, they will yield it much more Unlawful to act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Opining Conſcience in this ſence, which with them is a <hi>fixed Conſcience,</hi> either in <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil.</hi> And that it is unlawful to act againſt ſuch a Conſcience: <hi>Vaſquez</hi> is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, that he Diſputeth againſt <hi>Almainus,</hi> and <hi>Andreas de Caſtra,</hi> who had reſerved unto God a Liberty to diſpenſe with a Man acting againſt a <hi>fixed Conſcience, ſo as</hi> that a Man may do it without guilt; and contends, <hi>That God himſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſpenſe with it, becauſe it is an acting againſt the Law of Nature,</hi> Veſquez <hi>in</hi> 12. <hi>Diſp.</hi> 61. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>§. 6. There are [beſides Opinion] ſome other terms, Divines take Notice of: <hi>Suſpition,</hi> which they make the Jealouſie of the Mind, or ſome light Inclination to one part, yet without an Aſſent. <hi>Aquinas</hi> makes it the Younger Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an Opinion, and calls it an Opinion with a very <hi>light Evidence. Doubting</hi> is another, which they make the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulouſneſs of the Mind, as to the Lawfulneſs or Unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a thing after Debate. Now, from this variety of Propoſitions, and the variety of <hi>Mediums,</hi> through which a Light comes into our Minds, diſcovering the Truth, or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109403:7"/>Falſhood of them, and the variety of our aſſent conſequent to ſuch <hi>Mediums,</hi> ariſe the various Notions of a <hi>fixed Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. A Doubting Conſcience. An Opining Conſcience. A. Scrupulous Conſcience.</hi> Theſe are but the ſeveral Complexions of Conſcience, cauſed from the variety or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of that Light in which it ſeeth a Propoſition as true or falſe.</p>
               <p>§. 7. If the Matter in Queſtion be of that Nature, that it thinks it can find a plain, and particular Evidence for it in Scripture, or can judge of it by the certain Evidence of ſence, or ſee it in the certain Cauſes, the Conſcience is fixed, either <hi>truly,</hi> or <hi>erroneouſly;</hi> and (as to this thing) beareth the Name of a <hi>fixed,</hi> Good, or <hi>Erroneous Conſcience,</hi> as it is, or is not deceived in its apprehenſion of the <hi>Medium.</hi> If the Matter of the Propoſition, or that part to which the Soul ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hereth, be of that Nature, that the Soul cannot find a plain Revelation in Scripture, nor diſcern it by ſenſe, nor ſee it in the certain neceſſary Cauſes, but hath many <hi>probable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> rather for the one part than the other: Whether it thinks theſe Arguments Anſwerable or no, or thinks that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly they may be Anſwerable, but as yet it can ſee no Anſwer to them which it judgeth ſuſſicient; this now is an <hi>Opining Conſcience.</hi> If the Mind be equally ballanced on both ſides with Arguments, that it hath as much to ſay why ſuch a thing ſhould be Lawful, as why it ſhould be unlawful, or unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as Lawful; this is now a <hi>Doubting Conſcience,</hi> and rarely happeneth to a knowing and intelligent Soul. If the Soul be afraid, that this or that is <hi>not Lawful,</hi> or fancieth that ſuch a thing is Lawful, but hath none, or if any very light Reaſons for it, poſſibly ſuch or ſuch Men ſay ſo, or ſuch or ſuch Men do it, or do it not; this is a <hi>Suſpitious, or Scrupulous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 8. In ſhort, in Order to a Man's ſpotleſs walking. There are infinite Propoſitions to be weighed; God hath hung up a Beam, called <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in every individual Soul, in Order to the weighing of them; upon this Beam is written, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:109403:7"/>5.21. PROVE ALL THINGS, <hi>hold faſt that which is good.</hi> The Weights which God hath allowed us to weigh things by, are, Divine Revelation, Demonſtrations, Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Sence, Topicks or more probable Logical Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, made up from Logical places, and Concluſions for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from the comparing of <hi>Rational and Spiritual things</hi> 'tis Evident, with Rational or Spiritual things more Evident; when any of theſe fully weigh down the Souls aſſent, there's a <hi>Fixed Conſcience:</hi> When they equally incline the Balance one way, or another, there is a <hi>Doubting Conſcience.</hi> When <hi>they strongly incline</hi> the Soul more one way than another, ther's an <hi>Opining Conſcience.</hi> When they cauſe a very light inclination of the Soul to one part rather than to the other, there is a <hi>Suſpitious,</hi> or a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 9. Now, what the Duty of Chriſtians is, under theſe various Complexions of Conſcience, is a point, which hath juſtly exerciſed valuable Divines of all perſwaſions, for as we are capable by any of our Actions to incurr the wrath of God, ſo as to them generally, our Conſciences are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexionated, one way or another; for if we Act, we either do a thing, being <hi>fixedly</hi> perſwaded, it is Lawful, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, or <hi>doubting</hi> whether it be ſo, or <hi>ſtrongly inclined</hi> to think it is ſo or ſo; or <hi>ſuſpecting, and</hi> being ſcrupulous. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a Conſcience that is <hi>fixed</hi> in that which is <hi>truly good,</hi> none ever doubted of the Lawfulneſs of Acting according to it; or unlawfulneſs to Act againſt it: But concerning <hi>Conſcience</hi> in all the other Circumſtances, there have many Queſtions been ſtarted, as to the Truth in which the World is very far from being Univerſally agreed. <hi>Whether a Man may Act againſt a Conſcience fixed in an Error,</hi> is a Queſtion ſpoken to by moſt <hi>School-men</hi> and <hi>Caſuiſts.</hi> It is uſually ſaid, that ſuch a Conſcience doth <hi>Ligare non Obligare.</hi> It is not our buſineſs to diſpute, how well that diſtinction (Ordinarily Father'd upon <hi>Durandus,</hi>) is worded: but we do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, we ever met with any Deliberate Divine, that would affirm. <hi>That in caſe a Man were fully (though falſly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109403:8"/>perſwaded) that this or that thing was unlawful to be done, yet he might Lawfully do it.</hi> Though indeed (if the thing be a neceſſary Duty) he ſinneth in not doing it. <hi>Vaſquez</hi> ſaith, it is <hi>againſt the very Law of Nature. Sanchez</hi> ſaith, that although <hi>the Law of God be the primary Rule, yet every mans Conſcience is the proximate Rule of his Actions, and therefore be cannot Act againſt it.</hi> Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> ſaith, <hi>That he who doth it Interpretatively, ſins againſt God:</hi> For he muſt needs do contrary to what he believeth to be the will of God. <hi>Eilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius. tract.</hi> 21. <hi>M. Qu. c.</hi> 4. ſaith, <hi>That he which doth it, doth that which he thinketh to be ſin:</hi> And, ſaith he, <hi>hoc ipſo amat peccatum,</hi> by this thing he ſheweth he loveth to ſin, and chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſin. But this is not our Queſtion: We ſuppoſe a Man not to be fully and demonſtrably perſwaded, that this or that Action is unlawful, but onely upon Arguments, which ſeem to him very probable, verily to believe it is unlawful, and <hi>Quaery</hi> whether, while he ſo believeth he can do that thing. And this Queſtion divideth it ſelf, according to the different Notion of an Opinion which we before hinted, <hi>viz. Whether a Man thus perſwaded of the unlawfulneſs of an Action, by Arguments</hi> indeed, <hi>not demonſtrative, but ſuch as he judgeth very probable, and which he himſelf cannot Anſwer, ſo neither doth he think others can: may yet, becauſe his Principles are not Supernaturally, or Mathematically made certain to him, act against the Opinion of his own Conſcience, in Obedience to the will of any Creature.</hi> 2. <hi>Whether a Man thus perſwaded of the unlawfulneſs of any thing, by Arguments not demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> but <hi>probable</hi> (as before ſaid) <hi>though at preſent he can neither himſelf anſwer them, nor ſee them anſwered by any other; yet ſuſpecting they may be anſwered, may while this is the Condition of his Conſcience, act againſt the preſent judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, though it be incumbred with ſuch a Jealouſie or Suſpition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, as to the firſt of theſe Queſtions, we find little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſpoken in the Affirmative, by any <hi>Popiſh Caſuiſts, or School-men.</hi> They generally making <hi>ſome fear of the contrary part of</hi> the Practical Propoſition, to which the Perſon inclineth,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109403:8"/>and Jealouſie that this part of the propoſition is falſe, and <hi>his</hi> Arguments Anſwerable, eſſential to an <hi>Opinion,</hi> conclude, that a Soul perſwaded, though but upon probable Arguments (if it hath no ſuch fear, ſuſpition, or Jealouſie, to have a fixed Conſcience, and though fixed in an Error, yet conclude it utterly unlawful for a Man to Act againſt it. But if there be in any Soul any fear, ſuſpition, or Jealouſie, that its Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be Anſwered, then they conclude the Soul but Opining, and do indeed d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpute for a Lawfulneſs to Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, though under ſeveral <hi>Cautions</hi> and <hi>limitations.</hi> At this rebound therefore we will take the Queſtion, and ſtate it thus.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Whether, ſuppoſing a Man or Woman not Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strably perſwaded, that this or that Action is unlawful, but from arguments, which to him or her appear very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, verily believing ſo, yet not without ſome Jealouſie, Fear, or Suſpition that he may be miſtaken, and his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments may be anſwered: may, whiles he thus believes, do that thing in Obedience to Men, which in this manner he judgeth ſinful and unlawful to be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the clearer handling of this momentous, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Queſtion, we ſhall with all Candor Examine.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What Divines of all ſorts, whether Popiſh, or Proteſtant, have determined in the caſe, and upon what grounds?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>We ſhall endeavour to defend the Negative part of the Queſtion, proving it wickedneſs for any to act contrary to the judgment of their own Conſciences, though that Judgment be onely made up from intrinſick, probable arguments.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>We ſhall anſwer the Objections of thoſe, who have ſpoke any thing for the affirmative, with any colour of Reaſon.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:109403:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Opinions of Popiſh School-men, and Caſuiſts in the Caſe particularly of <hi>Vaſquez, Sanchez Medina, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liucius, Azorius.</hi> Their Monſtrous Aſſertions, what they make neceſſary to make an Opinion probable. The Opinion of one Doctor according to them ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to warrant Men to Act contrary to their own Opinions. Their Opinions what a Man ought to do, when Superiours Command Inferiours, what the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours judge unlawful. The ſumme of their deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Doctrine.</head>
               <p>§. 1. WE will begin with the Popiſh Authors. <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez</hi> tells us, that the Queſtion is not, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Man ought not to follow the Judgment of his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or could act againſt it;</hi> but when it happeneth, that there are two oppoſite Opinions about a thing to be done: One ſaying, it is a ſin to do it; another ſaith, it is not: <hi>The difficulty is, ſaith he, how a Man ſhould carry, himſelf betwixt them, ſo as to form up a ſingular Judgment of Conſcience, which without ſin he may embrace. Vaſquez in</hi> 12. <hi>diſp.</hi> 72. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. So then the Jeſuite (it ſeemeth) doth yield the caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That if once a Man hath formed a particular Judgment of Conſcience, that the thing is unlawful, though it be but from probable Arguments, he cannot do it, he onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes in a variety of Opinions in the World, as to a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Matter, how Men ſhould well form that Judgment. But not to wrong him in the 4. <hi>cap.</hi> of that Diſputation, <hi>n.</hi> 15. he ſeems to be of another mind, and aſſerteth. <hi>That a Man in ſome Caſes, may act contrary to his own Opinion, yea, that a Learned Man may Lawfully act contrary to his own Opinion, according to the Opinion of others, though it be leſs ſafe, and leſs probable than his own, provided there be any Reaſon and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109403:9"/>probability for the Opinion of thoſe others. Yet ſtill retaining his Opinion, as more probable, looking upon that Opinion of others; as probable by extrinſecal Arguments</hi> [that is the Authority, Judgments, and Teſtimony of others] <hi>though he judgeth his own Opinion more probable by intrinſick Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reaſons he gives for this, are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe we may act according to any Opinion which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth probable to us.</hi> We will anon Argue that Caſe, whether it be poſſible that any thing, from meer extrinſick Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can ſeem probable to a reaſonable Soul. The contrary to which at the ſame time ſeems probable from intrinſick Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments: But we know how far the <hi>Doctrine of Probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> ſerves the woful Intereſt of that <hi>Apoſtate Synagogue of Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>— Largo</l>
                  <l>Proventu eſt, gnavum non deceptura colonum.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Becauſe it ſeems incredible to be true, that a Man may not do what all the World judgeth Lawful, if he alone judgeth it unlawful.</hi> All the World, we confeſs, is a large term, and puts the Caſe to the higheſt pinch, but yet it ſeems not at all incredible, if that be true which the School-men Univerſally agree; <hi>That the particular Conſcience muſt be the proximate Rule of action:</hi> For what ſhall it profit a Man, more to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>all the World,</hi> than to gain <hi>all the World,</hi> if <hi>be loſeth his own Soul?</hi> A Man is certainly bound to follow his own Rules, not anothers. Theſe are that Jeſuites beſt Reaſons: He confeſſeth that in this he followeth <hi>Medina,</hi> ſome of whoſe Reaſons he yet rejects. Further, to make the Opinion of another <hi>probable</hi> to us, he requires,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That it be the Opinion of many; not one ſingle Doctor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That it be commonly Judged to contain no Error.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That we know that thoſe Doctors have conſidered, and Examined our Reaſons.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe things ſuppoſed, he thinks that although in a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109403:10"/>of Practice we have a more probable Opinion, and that from Arguments fetch'd from the Nature of the thing, and Scripture appearances, yet a Man may act contrary if others judge it is Lawful, yea, though he hath ſome fear, that that Opinion of others is not true: In which Caſe, both <hi>Cajetan</hi> and <hi>Navarrus</hi> (as he confeſſeth) differ from him: But he concludes it, <hi>ib. Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 26. provided that this fear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount not to a doubt or haeſitation (we wonder how that is poſſible to be avoyded) for in that Caſe, he avoweth it not Lawful to act contrary to our own Opinion, in Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with others. This is the Doctrine of <hi>Vaſquez</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina;</hi> and which <hi>Vaſquez</hi> ſaith is Common in the Schools.</p>
               <p>§. 2. <hi>Sanchez, Op. mor. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>n.</hi> 13. States the Queſtion thus: <hi>Whether it be Lawful for any to act accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Opinion of others which he judgeth probable, though in reſpect of the danger of ſin 'tis ſafe, againſt the Opinion of his own Conſcience which be judgeth more probable, and more ſafe.</hi> He confeſſeth that ſome deny it, becauſe of thoſe two Ordinary Rules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In dubiis animae tutior pars eſt eligenda,</hi> and <hi>Tene certum &amp; relinque incertum, i. e.</hi> In doubtful Caſes we ought to take the more certain part, and to leave what is more uncertain, and to hold what is certain. And again, <hi>Becauſe a Man cannot act againſt the dictate of his Conſcience.</hi> But <hi>Sanchez</hi> is himſelf of another mind, as he there declareth, <hi>viz. That it is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for a Man to act contrary to the Opinion of his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which he judgeth ſafeſt, according to the Opinion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which he judgeth leſs probably true, and leſs ſafe.</hi> Of this mind beſides <hi>Vaſquez and Medina</hi> (before mentioned by us) he ſaith are <hi>Mercado, Velentia, Julier, Suarez, Enriquez, Azorius, Bannes, Nauarrus, Arragon, Salon, Lopez, Ledeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, Salas, Sairus,</hi> and <hi>Leonardus.</hi> More than a full Jury, were they all good Men and true: But let us hear their ſtrong Reaſons. <hi>Sanchez</hi> gives us them thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Becauſe he who thus acteth, acteth according to Reaſon, and therefore his action is not to be charged with raſhneſs or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:109403:10"/>2. <hi>Becauſe in this caſe, a man may have a Moral certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Becauſe as that is a probable Opinion in matters of Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, which a man may embrace without danger of Error or deceit. So in Moral things, that Opinion is probable which a man may embrace without ſin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Becauſe it is onely ſinful to act doubting.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>§. 3. But is it poſſible that a reaſonable Soul ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand ſo wild ratiocinations? Suppoſe a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or at leaſt, one who hath been ſo bred, upon the Queſtion,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether there be Idolatry in the Maſs or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeth very probable intrinſecal Arguments to make him conclude, <hi>That the Maſs is Idolatrous,</hi> and that it is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for him to go to it any more. On the other ſide, he find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth many <hi>Doctors of their Church,</hi> poſitive, that it is not <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous,</hi> and that he may be <hi>preſent at it</hi> (we will ſuppoſe that they urge it, not as neceſſary, but only plead it Lawful.) Here now the private Opinion, is both <hi>more probable,</hi> and <hi>more ſafe. More probable</hi> it muſt be, becauſe it is a <hi>man's own Opinion,</hi> and that formed from intrinſick Arguments; ſo that to him it muſt be more probable. <hi>More ſafe</hi> it muſt be, ſuppoſing it be onely atteſted by others, as <hi>Lawful.</hi> We would fain know now whether under theſe Circumſtances, this Man may Lawfully go to <hi>Maſs</hi> againſt the <hi>dictate of his Conſcience.</hi> Yes (ſay they) for the Opinion of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors makes the contradictory part of the Propoſition <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble too.</hi> Poſſibly ſomething might be ſaid for this if the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon had no intrinſecal Arguments to incline him to the other part. But is not this Non-ſence to any Reaſonable Soul? That it ſhould judge <hi>contradictions</hi> both probably true; the one from one ſort of Arguments, the other from another ſort. Yet this is a <hi>Poſtulatum</hi> begg'd in the Caſe, both by <hi>Vaſquez</hi> and <hi>Sanchez,</hi> and all their Brethren; That one and the ſame thing, at the ſame time, and to the ſame Soul, upon differing Arguments, may appear in all probability <hi>Lawful</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> which we confeſs is a Riddle too hard for us;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109403:11"/>or we think any others but themſelves. But ſuppoſe this were poſſible, as both <hi>Sanchez</hi> and <hi>Vaſquez</hi> plead. Yet it is not Lawful for a Man to act according to the Opinion of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (ſaith <hi>Cajetan</hi> and <hi>Navarr</hi>) if he be in any fear that others are in the wrong; and though both <hi>Vaſquez</hi> and <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chez</hi> reject this, yet even they are ſo kind, as to grant, that the Perſon cannot act in this caſe, if he doth doubt. Now, we would fain know how a Man can poſſibly have intrinſick Arguments againſt what is propounded to him for Practice, and not <hi>haeſitare ac dubitare</hi> (which are their words) doubt at all, whether he may Lawfully act. Or how he can act with that <hi>Moral certainty</hi> which <hi>Sanchez</hi> ſpeaks of. Can a Man (think we) be Morally certain of that, againſt which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable intrinſecal Arguments, meerly becauſe others ſay the contrary. And this too, although what they ſay appear to the Perſon concerned both <hi>leſs probable,</hi> and <hi>leſs ſafe.</hi> What ſtrange Apprehenſions have theſe Men, both of themſelves, and of God?</p>
               <p>§. 4. <hi>Filiucius</hi> (another of the <hi>Popiſh Caſuiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>) telleth us. That it is Lawful to follow the <hi>more probable Opinion, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that which is leſs probable. Qu. mor. tr.</hi> 21. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 126. Compare this with what we heard <hi>Vaſquez</hi> even now ſaying. <hi>That a man's own Opinion is more probable</hi> (and ſo it muſt be to him, or he would never hold it.) The Caſe by this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion ſeems to be granted; but in the very next Paragraph he again concludeth, <hi>That it is alſo Lawful to follow the leſs probable Opinion, though it be leſs ſafe: and this he</hi> ſaith, is the Common Opinion of more Modern <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> and <hi>School-men,</hi> and quotes for it <hi>Medina, Vaſquez, Bannes,</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varrus;</hi> his Reaſon is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe whoſo doth ſo, acteth prudently, believing thoſe that are skill'd in that Art, and ſubmitting to their Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſaith well, if we were ſpeaking of Actions, as to which there is no danger of immediate ſinning, and running the guilt of Damnation, but he begs the Queſtion ſhamefully,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109403:11"/>while he averreth with <hi>Sanchez, That there is no danger of ſin in ſuch Actions;</hi> and one of his Brethren (with whom he is very angry for it) calleth this Opinion of his, and <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chez</hi> his ſeventeen Doctors <hi>Perni cioſae inſcitiae prolapſionem;</hi> a ſlip of perncious Ignorance: And he uſed him kindly too, for <hi>Prolapſio</hi> was doubtleſs too mild a word; it was unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably a <hi>wilful Error,</hi> but ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one as thoſe Learned Men ſaw neceſſary to be maintained, or the Doctrine of <hi>Blind Obedience</hi> could not ſtand.</p>
               <p>§ 5. <hi>Azorius, Inſtitut. Moral. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. In this Caſe determines, <hi>That we may follow an Opinion that is leſs certainly ſafe, if it be more probable or certain;</hi> from which we might conclude, that in regard the Opinion of our own Conſciences is always to us more probable and certain, than the Opinion of any other is, or can be, though there be a poſſibility of our ſinning in following our own, and no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility in following of anothers, yet we may follow it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He concludes, <hi>That if both Opinions be Equally ſafe, we are not bound to prefer that which is more probable.</hi> (Yet he confeſſeth, that <hi>Major, Corduba,</hi> and <hi>Medina</hi> think o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) he thinks the probability of an Opinion is enough to guide our Practice, and that we are not bound to follow that which is moſt probably true. But beſides that, ſome of his own Brethren tell him, and that truly, that <hi>That Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> which is (though not demonſtratively, yet <hi>moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly true</hi>) hath leaſt danger of ſin in it. Whether an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion can to any be <hi>probably true</hi> by extrinſick Arguments, which at the ſame time we judge from intrinſick Arguments probably not true, as Queſtion not yet reſolved. We do not at all doubt, but the <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of others may give a Propoſition ſome ſhew of Probability to be true. If we have no Arguments againſt what they ſay, from ſome appearances (at leaſt) of Scripture, or ſome Logical To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks. But when we have ſuch Arguments, that yet their Opinions in the contrary ſhould ſeem <hi>probable</hi> to us, is a great Riddle, and ſeems a great baffling of a Reaſonable Soul.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109403:12"/>Eſpecially conſidering that theſe Forreign Arguments are but Common, and may be brought in moſt Caſes on both ſides.</p>
               <p>§. 6. And indeed here all the Popiſh Doctors are at a great loſs, <hi>viz.</hi> To determine what thoſe Doctors muſt be; how many muſt concurr in an Opinion, before they may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule us in Practice, againſt the Judgment of our own Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces formed from proper intrinſecal Arguments. <hi>Sanchez</hi> ſaith, one Doctor is enough, and quotes on his ſide, <hi>Anges, Sylv. Navarrus, Valentia,</hi> and <hi>Sa;</hi> yea, and he proveth it by this Learned Argument: <hi>That is a probable Opinion which is not built upon a light Foundation. Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Opinion of one Doctor is not a light Foundation.</hi> Ay, but what if one Doctors Opinion be for us, another be againſt us? They will tell you, <hi>They are both probable.</hi> Take then the ſumme of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Doctrine.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>A probable Opinion is that, which is not built upon a light Foundation.</hi> (So ſaith <hi>Sanchez.</hi>)</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Any one Doctors Opinion is a conſiderable, and no light Foundation.</hi> That is <hi>Sanchez</hi> his medium.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Let a man have never ſo many intrinſecal, proper Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not demonſtrative, to prove a thing unlawful; yet he may do it if he can but find one Doctor who judgeth it Lawful.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>If one Doctor judgeth it Lawful, another judgeth it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, he may do what he pleaſeth in it, for both parts are probable.</hi> Hence <hi>Sanchez</hi> raiſeth theſe Concluſions.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <q>That if a Man, according to the Judgment of his own Conſcience, perfectly <hi>doubteth,</hi> from intrinſecal Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which in a practical caſe, he can find on the one ſide, or the other. Yet if he can from Extrinſecal Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>perſwade himſelf that either part is Lawful, he may do either.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>That he who probably judgeth it <hi>unlawful,</hi> to Act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a leſs probable Opinion, <hi>may yet Act</hi> according to that which he judgeth leſs probable, if he judgeth, <hi>That it is probably Lawful for him to follow that which is leſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:109403:12"/>3. <q>That Learned Men may adviſe others to act contrary to what themſelves, the Adviſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> think Lawful, if ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Doctor hath judged it Lawful.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, and many other damnable and abſurd Opinions they moſt impudently conclude, from theſe moſt wretched premiſes. And now, let any Judge, whether according to theſe Principles, there be any thing <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful or no;</hi> and one would think, that they do not judge any thing <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> that will but read their <hi>Eſcobar, Layman, Diaena, Filucius, Azorius, Sanchez.</hi> Or a breviate of ſome of their Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, p. 17. in the <hi>Additionals to the Myſtery of Jeſuitiſm,</hi> where he ſhall be directed alſo to the Authors.</p>
               <p>§. 7. But hitherto they have onely told us, what a Man <hi>May do:</hi> Let us hear ſhortly their Opinion of what Men <hi>Muſt do:</hi> and particularly, <hi>where Superiours Command us to act</hi> contrary to what we from proper intrinſecal Arguments judge Lawful. <hi>Adrianus,</hi> as he is quoted by <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> poſitively affirmeth, <hi>That none can Lawfully Obey their Superiours, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Opinion of his own Conſcience:</hi> he tells us alſo, That <hi>Corduba</hi> ſaith the ſame in effect, though he would ſave himſelf from this inconvenience by aſſerting, That what in it ſelf abſolutely conſidered, is evil, may by ſome Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances be good; as when it is neceſſary for us, of two evils, to chuſe one; here the leſſer evil is made good, comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that (ſaith he) is the Caſe here (<hi>Vaſquez</hi> 12. <hi>diſp.</hi> 62. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.) <hi>It is an evil thing for a man to act contrary to the opinion of his own Conſcience. And it is an evil thing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey our Superiours,</hi> but one of theſe we muſt do; in this caſe, ſaith he, <hi>It is Lawful for a man to act</hi> againſt his own <hi>opinion, in obedience to his Superiours;</hi> thus far the <hi>Jeſuite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Man might have expected ſuch an unboyled Meſs of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity from a <hi>John of Leiden,</hi> or a <hi>Knipperdolling;</hi> but is this ſpoken like Divine? <hi>Can there then be any neceſſity of ſinning?</hi> (where's Man's free-will in the mean time?) doth God ever bring the Soul into ſuch a ſtrait? Is it not a known Rule, <hi>That of two evils of puniſhment, we may indeed chuſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109403:13"/>the leaſt; but of two evils of ſin, none?</hi> An Erroneous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience indeed is under a neceſſity of ſinning, but ſurely he hath no choice in the caſe, whether he will ſin this way, or that way, but muſt follow the dictate of his Conſcience, Whether the diſtinction of <hi>Ligat, non obligat</hi> be worth any thing or no; ſurely all will ſay, he cannot Act againſt his fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>erring</hi> Conſcience. Is it not a known Rule, <hi>That nothing can be made good by a Circumſtance,</hi> though indeed Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may make a thing evil, becauſe <hi>Bonum eſſe Cauſis integris Malum e quolibet defectu.</hi> Therefore <hi>Vaſquez</hi> (who <hi>Diana</hi> ſaith, <hi>is inſtar omnium</hi>) explodes this Doctrine of <hi>Corduba,</hi> telling us truly, <hi>That the Obedience which any Man oweth to his Superiours, ſuppoſeth the matter of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors Command, not to be contrary to the Command of one who is higher than he; for in ſuch Caſes no Obedience is due, nor is it any ſin to diſobey,</hi> viz. where the thing <hi>required, is contrary to the Law of Nature, the Law of God,</hi> or <hi>the Law of a Superiour in an higher Order.</hi> Again, it is very poſſible (as <hi>Vaſquez</hi> ſaith) that it may be a greater ſin to contradict my own Conſcience, than not to Obey my Superiours, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing my Conſcience telleth me the thing required is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Law of Nature.</p>
               <p>But yet <hi>Vaſquez</hi> himſelf thinketh, that in caſe the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Commandeth, a thing otherwiſe <hi>probably Lawful</hi> (that is, as we before heard, which ſome Doctor or Doctors judge ſo) then it is Lawful for a Man to Obey contrary to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Opinion of his own Conſcience, <hi>becauſe he might do it in ſuch caſe, though it were not Commanded;</hi> and this is his Principle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That when the Precept of a Superiour may Lawfully be Obeyed, he is then bound to do it, and it becomes neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This indeed is a ſtrong Argument, if we could yield the premiſes, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That a Man may Lawfully contrary to the probable Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his own Conſcience, follow the Opinion of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Quod adhuc eſt Demonſtrandum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:109403:13"/>We ſhall anon ſhew the Curſed Fruit of this Root, yet <hi>Vaſquez</hi> limiteth this Doctrine a little, by telling us,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Superiour must be unqueſtionably our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Subject muſt know, and believe, that the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirour Commandeth according to a probable Opinion, and must not think it probable, meerly becauſe he is his Superiour; for</hi> (ſaith he) The Dignity of the Superiour Commanding, doth not make an Opinion probable. Thus far now we have heard the Judgment of the <hi>Popiſh Caſuists</hi> and <hi>School-men</hi> in this Caſe. The Summe is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is Lawful for a Man to do, what his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from intrinſick, probable Arguments judgeth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, if one or more Doctors do but Judge it Lawful, and in ſuch Caſes, if the Superiour Commandeth, he is bound to do what he in his own Conſcience judgeth unlawful, if it be not apparently, and demonſtratively ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How near this comes to the Sentiments of ſome Modern <hi>Proteſtant Doctors,</hi> we may enquire hereafter, but before we come to that, let us enquire what the Ancienter Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants have judged in the Caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:109403:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Opinion of former Proteſtants, about the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or unlawfulneſs of Mens Acting contrary to the Opinion of their own Conſciences. Such Acting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by all former Proteſtant Caſuiſts. <hi>Bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus, Alſtedius, Ameſius, Perkins:</hi> The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of ſome later Divines from their Fore-Fathers, particularly, Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi> The Vanity of his Proof, from <hi>Deut. 17.18. Acts 15.</hi> Or from Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> agreeing with Ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. So Mr. <hi>Fulwood,</hi> in his Caſes. The differing Expreſſions of ſome Divines of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Age, The tender touching of the Queſtion, and nibbling at the Opinion of the Popiſh Doctors in the Caſe by others. The Queſtion again ſtated, and made ready for Debate.</head>
               <p>§. 1. WE will begin with <hi>Fredericus Baldvinus,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor at <hi>Wittenbergh,</hi> he, in his Caſes, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. Profeſſedly diſputeth this great point, he takes No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the two ſorts of pretended probable Arguments, and determineth, in reference to both.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That an Opinion onely raiſed from the multitude of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Teſtimonies in the Caſe, bindeth no Man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That an Opinion taken up upon probable Reaſons, doth bind, and ſo bind, that a man cannot Act againſt it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>His words in Latine are theſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Cùm ergo opinionem aliquam, non ob aſſenſum aliorum, ſed ob cauſas probabiles pro verâ habes. Obligatus es in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiâ ne contra eam agas, licet Superiores aliud a te exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, donec rationes veriores audias in contrarium, ad quas tamen audiendas ſemper paratus eſſe debes: Et opinionem
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109403:14"/>tuam auditâ meliore ſententiâ deponere.</hi>
                  </q> That is,</p>
               <p>When thou haſt taken up any Opinion for true, not for the Teſtimony of others, but for probable Reaſons, thou art bound in Conſcience not to act againſt it; no, not though Superiours require thee to act, till thou heareſt better Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the contrary: To hear which thou oughteſt to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready, and lay down thy Opinion, hearing a better. The Opinion of this <hi>Grave</hi> and Learned <hi>Profeſſor</hi> is what we take it, &amp; will be found to have been the Opinion of all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of former Ages. For, the Obſerving Reader will find, as to this point, the ſame proportionable difference betwixt Ancient Proteſtant Divines, and a Modern brood, as betwixt the <hi>Old Fathers</hi> and <hi>School-men,</hi> and the later <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> who have traded in <hi>Scholaſtical,</hi> and <hi>Moral Divinity.</hi> The latter profeſſing wholly to differ from the former: We ſhall, I ſay, find, that all former Proteſtants have agreed, <hi>That although he that is poſſeſſed of an opinion, that the thing which is by his Superiours required, is unlawful, out of Reverence to his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, ought throughly to Examine his Opinion, and to hear better Reaſons, if they can be brought, and being by them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, to lay down his opinion: Yet while he can do that, he cannot do the thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 2. Let us, in the next place, enquire of <hi>Alſtedius.</hi> He diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth concerning <hi>Opinion,</hi> as relating to a more External Court, or to the Court of Conſcience: As to the former, he ſaith, <hi>In Diſputations,</hi> &amp;c.<hi>the Common Opinion is to be preferred before our own.</hi> But as to Conſcience, he ſaith, <hi>Whatſoever is done againſt our Conſciences, is ſinful; whether our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be Erring, Opining, or Rightly informed. vid. Theol. caſuum, cap.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 2. Dr. <hi>Ames, caſ. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. determines, <hi>That it is never Lawful for the Authority of other Men to act againſt our own Opinion, be it certain, or onely probable.</hi> We do not remember more than four <hi>Proteſtant Caſuiſts</hi> we had, whoſe Writings are more than forty Years Old. Theſe were three, the fourth was Judicious Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> who ſeems to reduce this to a doubting Conſcience, and determines,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109403:15"/>
                  <hi>That it is ſin to act againſt it, becauſe he cannot act in Faith, if his Conſcience be doubting, or erring, or gain-ſaying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe being all our former Divines, who wrote Treatiſes of Caſes, further Teſtimony is not to be expected. It were eaſie to produce multitudes collaterally ſpeaking the ſame things. But for them, we ſhall but refer the Reader to any <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that have formerly wrote upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. and ſee what they ſay upon theſe words; <hi>Whoſo doubteth, is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if he eateth, becauſe he eateth not of Faith: For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not of Faith, is ſin.</hi> And v. 5. <hi>Let every Man be fully perſwaded in his oven mind;</hi> he will find enough, we paſs it over, intending our ſelves to make ſome uſe of that Text anon.</p>
               <p>§. 3. But (as we ſaid before) look as in this very point there is a very great difference, betwixt the <hi>Ancient Fathers</hi> and <hi>School-men</hi> and the Modern <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> in ſo much, that the latter will not allow the Judgment of any of the Ancients, in theſe Caſes; and both <hi>Vaſquez</hi> and <hi>Sanchez</hi> think fit to Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their Readers againſt it, and both <hi>Cellot</hi> and <hi>Reginaldus</hi> expreſly determine: <hi>That in Moral Queſtions, the Modern Caſuiſts are to be preferred before the Ancient Fathers, though they lived nearer the times of the Apoſtles.</hi> So we ſhall Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that ſome later <hi>Proteſtant Divines</hi> have delivered themſelves, either ſomething odly, or expreſly contrary to the Sentiments of all <hi>Ancient Proteſtants in this caſe.</hi> Let us hear now what they ſay.</p>
               <p>§. 4. The Learned Author of the Eccleſiaſtical Polity, Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> in his Preface to it, directed <hi>To ſuch as ſeek Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> perſwading thoſe whom in that <hi>Preface</hi> he is Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to <hi>an end</hi> of Controverſie, concludeth it not poſſible to be obtained.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Without ſubmitting to ſome judicial and definitive Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, whereunto neither part that contendeth may under any pretence, or colour refuſe to stand: — Ways of peaceable concluſion</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>there are but two certain: The one a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109403:15"/>Sentence of Judicial deciſion, given to Authority there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appointed within our ſelves. The other, the like kind of Sentence, given by a more <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Authority. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of which God himſelf in the Law preſcribeth: And his Spirit it was which directed the firſt Chriſtian Churches in the World to uſe the latter: this he proves by</hi> Deut. 17.8. and Acts 15. (both which we will examine anon.) Afterward he comes in with this paſſage. <hi>Neither wiſh we, that Men ſhould do any thing which in their Hearts they are perſwaded they ought not to do; but this perſwaſion ought, we ſay, to be</hi> fully ſettled <hi>in their Hearts.</hi> That in Litigious and controverted Caſes of ſuch Quality, The Will of God is to have them to do, whatſoever the Sentence of Judicial and final deciſion ſhall determine. Yea, though it ſeemeth in their private Opinion, utterly to ſwerve from that which is right. as no doubt many times the Sentence amongſt the Jews did ſeem unto one part or another contending, and yet in this Caſe God did not then allow them to do what in their private Judgment it ſeemed, yea, and perhaps, truly ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Law did diſ-allow.</q> This paſſage muſt be a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle examined, eſpecially at ſuch a time when there is ſuch a ſtrict ſcrutiny upon thoſe who ſeem to have their Faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Rome;</hi> for as on the one ſide, if this Doctrine be not true, Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> neither in his <hi>Preface,</hi> nor in his bulky Book (thoſe Oracles we are ſo Ordinarily ſent to) hath ſaid much to perſwade thoſe whom he treated, <hi>That it is their Duty to conform;</hi> and our late Writers have ſaid much leſs, who have thought to <hi>jeer,</hi> and <hi>rail,</hi> and <hi>Hector</hi> Men out of their Religion, and have indeed all built upon this Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on [If the thing be not <hi>Demonſtratively evil,</hi> or as others <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently evil.</hi>] On the other ſide, if this be true, and be not very cautiouſly expounded, it over-throweth all <hi>Old Practical Divinity,</hi> and takes away what we doubt whether ever any conſiderate Learned Man ever denyed, <hi>viz. That the Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Conſcience is the proximate Rule of all our Actions.</hi> It ſheweth a neceſſity of an <hi>Infallible Judge;</hi> or if not ſo, moſt certainly eſtabliſheth <hi>Blind Obedience,</hi> the very <hi>Baſis</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109403:16"/>Pillar of <hi>Popery;</hi> yea, of <hi>Jeſuitiſme</hi> (the worſt of Popery. (for what is <hi>Blind Obedience,</hi> but an Obeying of Superiours contrary to the Light of our own Reaſon and Conſcience.) Nay, more, it is a peg beyond the Doctrine of <hi>Vaſquaez, Sanchez, Azorius, Layman,</hi> or the boldeſt Jeſuite who ever wrote.</p>
               <p>§. 5. I can ſee but two terms, which can be ſuppoſed to regulate this Learned Man' ſence by any Sobriety. He ſaith, onely [in litigious and controverted Cauſes of ſuch Quality] he ſhould have done well to have told us, of <hi>what Quality,</hi> and what makes <hi>a litigious</hi> and <hi>controverted Caſe?</hi> Whether ſome few, or more mens denying, or controverting, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting a points? For elſe ſuppoſe that in <hi>France,</hi> the King ſhould Command his Proteſtant Subjects to go to Maſs; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s <hi>Divinity,</hi> they are bound to go: why? For (ſaith he) <hi>It is the Will of God that they ſhould, in litigious and controverted Cauſes do whatſoever the Sentence of judicial and final deciſion ſhall determine.</hi> But will ſome Advocate for Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> ſay, the Proteſtants judge going to Maſs unlawful. What then? It followeth in Mr. <hi>Hooker. Though in their private Opinion it ſeem to ſwerve utterly from that which it right. Sit anima noſtra cum Philoſophis;</hi> Commend us to the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> for none of them ſpeak ſo broad. And it in well worth the Obſerving, what Excellent uſe <hi>Serenus Creſſy</hi> hath made of this very paſſage, in his Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Pierce</hi> his Sermon, and indeed it is very improveable for their turn. Shall thoſe blind words, <hi>Of ſuch Quality,</hi> help this Father of Conformity: The Queſtion recurs, Of what Quality? Can any other Quality of Caſes be here conſiderable, but either as the things appear <hi>Lawful, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> or <hi>Indifferent.</hi> If he means, in Caſes appearing to the Perſon, <hi>Lawful</hi> or <hi>Indifferent,</hi> the thing is granted: But it is impoſſible this ſhould be his meaning, for he ſaith, <hi>Though the Command ſeem to him utterly to ſwerve from what is right,</hi> If therefore the word, <hi>Seem,</hi> will not help him, he is not to be helped, but muſt be affirmed to have made
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109403:16"/>the <hi>boldeſt overture</hi> for <hi>Blind Obedience</hi> (the moſt bruitiſh piece of Popery) that ever Proteſtant made; and let our Brethren ſend us no more for Conſcience-ſatisfaction to Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> till they can defend him in this <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> and when they have done that, they will have paved his <hi>Holineſs</hi> a fairer way into all Proteſtant Tents, than he ever yet had. Indeed there are various degrees of <hi>Seeming.</hi> A thing may ſeem to us to ſwerve from what is right, meerly from <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick Arguments,</hi> becauſe we Reverence the <hi>Learning,</hi> or <hi>Piety</hi> of ſome that ſay ſo; in this ſence it may be true: But this cannot be <hi>Hookers Sence;</hi> for he ſaith, <hi>In his own private Opinion.</hi> But his meaning muſt be, <q>That we ought to be fully perſwaded, that in all Litigious, and Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Caſes reſerring to Practice. It is the Will of God that Chriſtians ſhould do, whatſoever the Sentence of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial and final deciſion ſhall determine, though that thing determined ſeem to the Perſon required to do it, and that from proper intrinſick Arguments (if not demonſtrative) in the Chriſtians private Opinion, to be quite contrary to what God's Law requireth of him.</q> Which is a poſition ſo contrary. To <hi>the Law of Nature, the whole Current of Scripture, the force of Reaſon, the Liberty of a Chriſtian, and the Judgment of all Proteſtant Divines,</hi> that it will ask very good Proof before we ſhall believe a tittle of it true.</p>
               <p>§. 6. He offereth a double Proof of it. 1. <hi>Becauſe</hi> he ſuppoſeth <hi>there muſt be an end of Controverſie,</hi> and that can be no other way. 2. <hi>Becauſe of the Law of God of Old,</hi> Deut. 17.8. and <hi>the determination of the Council,</hi> Acts 15. <hi>guided, no queſtion, by the Spirit of God.</hi> We will conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both. As to the firſt; Controverſies are of ſeveral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. There are <hi>Political Controverſies,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Controverſies;</hi> and theſe either relating to Matters of meer Speculation or Practice. And there are mixed <hi>Controverſies,</hi> partly of a <hi>Civil,</hi> partly of a <hi>Religious concern.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. For <hi>Civil Controverſies,</hi> they are of ſeveral Natures; for many of them it is abſolutely neceſſary, in Order to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109403:17"/>conſiſtency of Polities; there ſhould be an end of them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the end of ſome of them, the Order of Juſtice cannot bold; nor Kingdoms and States be preſerved: As now, ſuppoſe a Controverſie about the Title of the Supreme Magiſtrate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There muſt be an end to theſe, and it muſt be by one parties ſubmiſſion to the final deciſion of ſome power. Men may do it without ſinning againſt God: And it is the will of God, even written in Nature, that they ſhould do it. Suppoſe there be a plea betwixt Man, and Man, concerning a right of Inheritance, and they have had a long Suit about it; there muſt be an end to this Controverſie, and the end muſt be by a ſubmiſſion of one party to the final deciſion (at leaſt) of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court of Juſtice in a Nation; Beyond which lyes no appeal. What further can be done, unleſs this private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould take up Arms againſt this Court, and ſo diſturb all Civil Orders? nor ſhall he who ſuffers in this Judgment need fear ſinning againſt God, by parting with his Inheritance, no Law of God Obligeth him to keep it. He is before this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at perfect Liberty to part with it, and by this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it becomes neceſſary: We fear that we ſhall anon find the Text, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. Concerning ſuch Controverſies; and ſo nothing to the purpoſe in our Caſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But there are other Controverſies, which are in Matters of meer <hi>Speculation,</hi> or <hi>Practice.</hi> Some things there are, which are meerly Speculative, which infer no Practice, which ſide ſoever we take; as now, <hi>Whether the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>lived, and dyed a Virgin,</hi> &amp;c. For theſe Controverſies, we know no need of an end of them, nor why they ſhould be Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; Men may Opine one thing or another in them, without hazard to their Souls. There are other Controverſies in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which being determined, require of us, either an Act of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Aſſent</hi> from us, as our Duty, or more, <hi>i.e.</hi> the guidance of our Converſation, according to our belief. And theſe again are either ſuch as are <hi>Fundamentally neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> or <hi>ſuch as are not ſo neceſſary.</hi> As now, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that, <hi>Whether Jeſus Chriſt be the Eternal Son of God,</hi> is Matter of Controverſie betwixt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> the <hi>Socinians,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:109403:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>the <hi>Orthodox. Whether a Man may Lawfully adore the bread in the Eucharist,</hi> is Controverted betwixt the <hi>Papiſts and Proteſtants.</hi> It is neceſſary that the Magiſtrate or Church ſhould put an end to theſe Controverſies, at leaſt, as to the evulging of them, becauſe there is a part in them ſo neceſſary to be believed, or done, as Men's Salvation dependeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it immediately; and thoſe entruſted with the Charge of Souls, ſtand Obliged by the Law of Charity, as much as in them lyeth to obviate their eternal Ruine. But there are a third ſort of Controverſies in Religion, which relate to Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, <hi>in thoſe things, where Gods Word hath left nothing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> determined.</hi> Such Controverſies there ever was, and ever will be in the Church. But as it is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Corruption of Men,</hi> which makes theſe Controverſies (for why ſhould any Quarrel with his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for uſing his own Latitude, where God hath determined nothing?) So there is no need to put an end to them, but onely to Mens Luſts and Paſſions in the Arguing of them. For there is no hazard of Salvation, either one way or other. We dare be bold to ſay, that the ſilly humour of ſome, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it neceſſary, that all Men ſhould ſay, <hi>It is a Hen-Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> when ſome think it a <hi>Cock-Sparrow.</hi> Or write [it] when ſome think it is better wrote [yt] Or that all Men ſhould keep and <hi>Eaſter-day;</hi> ſuch a day, when as others think it not the right, hath been the cauſe of ſo much ſin and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, ſo much Blood and Cruelty, as all that theſe Humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts are worth, is no way able to recompence, either to Gods Glory, the Churches Peace, or the Profit and <hi>Advantage of Princes</hi> ſo infinitely hindred by it</p>
               <p>§. 7. We ſuppoſe, <hi>Peace</hi> will be urged as neceſſary to put an end to Controverſie. And is there no other way to obtain it, but by Mens doing <hi>quite contrary to what they Judge right?</hi> The Apoſtle hath ſhewed Men a nearer way to it, if their Luſts would let them ſee it, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15, 16. What a ſtrange fancy it is that there ſhould be no way to Peace, but what is impoſſible, <hi>viz.</hi> Mens perſwading themſelves, <hi>That it is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109403:18"/>the Will of God, that in ſuch Caſes they ſhould do whatſoever Men determine, though in their own Opinion it ſeems quite to ſwerve from what is right:</hi> As if there were no way to keep a Man from burning his ſhins, but by pulling down a Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and ſetting it further off. This is a ſad end. His <hi>Moſt Excellent Majeſty</hi> hath ſhewed them a quicker End, <hi>viz. Not Enacting the doing of ſuch things of thoſe who judge them <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful; but leaving them to their Liberty;</hi> and onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring, as the Apoſtle, in ſuch Caſes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 2. <hi>That he who eateth ſhould not deſpiſe him that eateth not; nor he who eateth not, deſpiſe him that eateth.</hi> Could our Brethren be quiet, and not repreſent us to the World, as <hi>Factious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Schiſmaticks; unreaſonable, ungovernable, Dunces,</hi> we wonder what hindred Peace now.</p>
               <p>§. 7. But, ſaith Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> (and he is the <hi>Delphick Oracle</hi> it ſeems in this Caſe) <hi>He muſt needs perſwade himſelf, That it is the Will of God, That in Litigious and Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Caſes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he ſhould ſubmit to the Deciſion of his Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, though in his own Opinion it ſeems quite to ſwerve from that which is right.</hi> We would fain know how he ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelf of this. This perſwaſion cannot be of <hi>Faith;</hi> for where doth the Word of God ſpeak a tittle to this ſence? It ſpeaks the contrary, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5.23. How ſhall we know a thing to be either according contrary to the Will of God. Certainly we muſt know it from Nature, or from <hi>Divine Revelation.</hi> Doth the Light of Nature ſhew us any ſuch thing? Indeed in Controverſies of a Civil Nature, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of which the Light of Nature ſhews us muſt be by Superiours, and where a ſubmiſſion is neceſſary, and not to be avoyded, without diſturbance of Polities, and all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Juſticer: The Light of Nature may ſhew us ſome ſuch thing. But certainly, where the Light of Nature ſheweth us no need of a Controverſie, nor of determining it, if there muſt be one, it can ſhew us nothing as to the Will of God, for a ſubmiſſion to ſuch <hi>Determination.</hi> Nor indeed is it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and it were ſtrange if it ſhould, when the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109403:18"/>determine, <hi>That Acting againſt an erroneous Conſcience</hi> (much more Opining) <hi>is againſt the Light of Nature.</hi> This piece of the Will of God then which we muſt (ſaith Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>) perſwade our ſelves of, muſt be from <hi>Revelation,</hi> and that is either <hi>New</hi> (ſome Enthuſiaſm) or Old, which is the Word of God. Where ſhall we find ſuch a piece of the revealed Will of God in Scripture? Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> tells us, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 15. we will Examine both theſe Texts.</p>
               <p>§. 8. The words in <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If there ariſe a Matter too hard for thee in Judgment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Blood and Blood, betwixt plea and plea, betwixt ſtroke and ſtroke, being matters of Controverſie within thy Gates. Then ſhalt thou ariſe, and get thee up unto the place which the Lord thy God ſhall chuſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And thou ſhalt come unto the Prieſts, the Levites, and unto the Judge who ſhall be in thoſe days, and enquire, and they ſhall ſhew the Sentence of Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And thou ſhalt do according to the Sentence which they of that place, which the Lord ſhall chuſe, ſhall ſhew thee: and thou ſhalt Obſerve to do according to all that they ſhall inform thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>According to the Sentence of the Law which they ſhall teach thee, and according to the Judgment which they ſhall tell thee, thou ſhalt do, thou ſhalt not decline from the Sentence which they ſhall ſhew thee, to the right hand, nor to the left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Man that will do preſumptuouſly, and will not hearken unto the Prieſt, that ſtandeth up to Miniſter before the Lord thy God, or unto the Judge, even that Man ſhall dye, and thou ſhalt put away evil from</hi> Iſrael. Theſe words are fully that Text. As to which, we deſire our Reader to Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this is <hi>Bellarmines</hi> firſt Text to prove <hi>Blind Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> the Duty of Chriſtians: So that we may eaſily judge, which way the Face of theſe Diſputants doth ſtand. It might ſuffice but to refer our Reader to <hi>Chamer,</hi> or any that have
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109403:19"/>Anſwered <hi>Bellamine,</hi> for an Anſwer to this Objection.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> In caſe this Text will ſerve the turn now, it will infallibly prove the Lawfulneſs of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Judges put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to death ſuch as ſhall not do what they have once determined in any caſe, that is indifferent of it ſelf, and once by them made neceſſary.</hi> But ſurely this muſt be aſſerted by none that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue their words at any rate. But to come cloſe to the Text; if any Argument in this caſe can be drawn from it, it muſt be this.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>What the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were bound to do, upon any deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination by the Prieſt or Judge in the place where the Lord ſhould chuſe: In hard Matters, between plea and plea, blood and blood. That Chriſtians under the Goſpel are bound to do, upon the final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the Prieſt or Judge, in hard matters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween plea and plea, blood and blood, treſpaſs and treſpaſs, ſtroke and ſtroke.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were bound to do according to the final deciſion of the Prieſt or Judge, ſitting in the place which the Lord ſhould chuſe, and Judging in hard Matters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Plea and Plea, Blood and Blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>If the Argument be thus laid, it concludeth nothing like the Queſtion, but is <hi>tranſitus degenere in genus.</hi> Our Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is not about Civil things in Controverſie, where a Man may take any part, and not ſin againſt God, and where <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> onely inferreth <hi>Suſſering</hi> in matters of a temporal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, but about Religious Actions, where a Practice is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, which the Party Commanded Judgeth ſinful: And hazarding the damnation of his Soul. Whence alſo it may be Obſerved, That no Concluſion can from hence be fetched from any purity of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>But if Mr. <hi>Booker</hi> intends from that Text to conclude the Queſtion, his Argument muſt be laid thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>What the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were bound to, as to hard Caſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, in Judgment betwixt plea and plea, blood and blood, treſpaſs and treſpaſs, ſtroke and ſtroke. That Chriſtians are bound to do, in all Litigious Controverted Caſes of Religion; or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109403:19"/>(at leaſt) in ſuch Caſes where the Superiours Judge the things, by them Commanded, to be in themſelves of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Nature.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the</hi> Iſraelites, <hi>in hard Caſes in Judgment, betwixt plea and plea, Blood and Blood, treſpaſs and treſpaſs, ſtroke and ſtroke, were Obliged to do according to, and not decline from the Sentence of the Law, which the Prieſts, the Levites, or the Judges ſhould teach them, and according to the Judgment, which they ſhould ſhew them, though in the Opinion of their own Conſciences it ſwerved utterly from that which was right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ergo. <hi>Chriſtians alſo under the Goſpel, in all Litigiout con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Caſes, eſpecially of ſuch Quality, where the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Judgeth the things indifferent, are bound to do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to, and not to decline from the Sentence of the Law, which the Civil or Eccleſiaſtical Superiours, now adays ſhall teach them; though in the Opinion of their own Conſciences it utterly ſwerveth from that which is right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which we Anſwer, 1. The whole concludeth nothing to the purpoſe, for it concludeth not that they ought to do any thing <hi>contrary to the Sentence of the Divine Law.</hi> That was of Old to the Prieſts <hi>a Regula Regulans;</hi> an Original Rule, and muſt be ſo, to all Superiours; and it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble any ſhould be Obliged to Act contrary to it. But, leſt any ſhould ſay, they were bound to take <hi>the Prieſts and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites,</hi> and <hi>Judges Sentence,</hi> to be the Sentence of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law, we further Anſwer.</p>
               <p>§. 9. By denying the <hi>Major,</hi> which is moſt notoriouſly falſe, and before it can be made good, thoſe that inherit Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s Spirit, muſt make good theſe things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That there it the ſame Reaſon, or Equity for Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours final deciſion, and a Chriſtians ſubmiſſion as to his Practice, to a final deciſion in things of a Religious Nature, which the Superiour Judgeth indifferent, and the Inferiour, (from Arguments which in the Judgment of his particular Conſcience, ſeem probable) judgeth unlawful. As there was for a final
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109403:20"/>deciſion amongſt the Jews, and their ſubmiſſion to ſuch deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in Matters between Blood and Blood, plea and plea, treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs and treſpaſs, ſtroke and ſtroke;</hi> which apparently there is not, a determination in the latter being abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for upholding the Beings of <hi>Polities,</hi> the Courſe, and Order of Juſtice, the preſervation of Humane Society, and not making the World a Den of Thieves and Murtherers. But no ſuch things can be pretended for things in Religion, by the Superiours owned in their own Nature, but indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and ſo left by God. Neither is there the ſame Equity or Reaſon for the <hi>Inferiours Submiſſion.</hi> For what harm could the Inferiour have by ſubmitting to the final deciſion of the <hi>Prieſts, Levites,</hi> and <hi>Judges,</hi> in thoſe Civil things? He might poſſibly be inforced to put up a wrong, to part with a little Money, or with ſome part of his Inheritance, or ſuffer in caſe of <hi>Blood</hi> operatly, which was his due by a Divine Law: He was in no danger, by ſuch ſubmiſſion, of damning his Soul, or wounding his Conſcience by finning againſt God; though he might judge he were ſeverely, or unrighteouſly dealt with. He might poſſibly think the part contrary to the deciſion <hi>more juſt and right:</hi> But what was he to do? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but part with his own Right in Temporal things for the ſake of publick Juſtice, and Order, and Peace, which is every good Chriſtians Duty, and Choice: But here we are required to do ſome things, and that in ſo tender a thing, as Divine Worſhip; which if we do, we ſhall wound our Conſciences, run the hazard of Damnation by ſinning, ſo far as we can apprehend it. Can any one in his wits now judge theſe two Caſes alike? If not, the Propoſition is falſe. There is a manifeſt Tranſition in the Argumentation from the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of things of one kind, to prove the Lawfulneſs of things of a quite different <hi>Kind, Nature,</hi> and <hi>Influence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 10. Further, to make good the Propoſition, it muſt be proved, <hi>That God hath under the Goſpel erected ſuch a Court, for the final deciſion of all Litigious and Controverted Caſes of like Quality.</hi> For certain it is that Old Court is down;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109403:20"/>where is the Law Erecting the New? Nay, where are the Perſons ſo Qualified for it? Thoſe who know any thing, know that the High-Prieſts amongſt the Jews had any <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> and ſo were hardly (in their Judicature) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Fallibility, to be ſure, leſs than any now under the Goſpel. It was at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> or at <hi>Siloh,</hi> at the place <hi>the Lord was to chuſe,</hi> where the Ark was, and the Linnen <hi>Ephod,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> that this bending Judgment was to be made, no where elſe. Beſides, all know that their High-Prieſt: was the <hi>Type of Chriſt,</hi> who is <hi>The Truth;</hi> and to whom alone now we reſerve Infallibility.</p>
               <p>The Papiſts have a better plea in this Caſe than any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, becauſe they have provided for it, by Creating to themſelves an <hi>Infallible Judge,</hi> and, at leaſt, cheating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſuch a previous Foundation fit to Build ſuch a Structure upon.</p>
               <p>§. 11, We have ſhewed the vanity of Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s plea from the Law, let us ſee now what he ſaith from the Goſpel. He Obſerves, that under that, the Spirit of God directed a Court for <hi>Final deciſion,</hi> Acts 15. The Caſe was this, <hi>Some who came from</hi> Judea, <hi>had taught the Brethren,</hi> that unleſs they were Circumciſed, they could not be ſaved; upon this, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were ſent, with others, to meet and conſult <hi>with the Apoſtles and Elders at</hi> Hieruſalem <hi>about this Matter.</hi> Hear their Reſolution, <hi>v.</hi> 28. <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghost, and to us, to lay upon you no greater burthen than theſe neceſſary things; That you abſtain from Meats of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Idols, and from things ſtrangled, and from Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from which if you ſhall keep your ſelves, you ſhall do well.</hi> That in multiplying word we may not loſe our Propoſition from hence to be proved, it will not be amiſs here to repeat it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is the Will of God, that in all Litigious, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Caſes of this Quality.</hi> (Suppoſe where the Superiour Judgeth the thing Commanded in its own Nature, indifferent, though the Inferiour from
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109403:21"/>Arguments which to him ſeem probable, judgeth them unlawful) <hi>that Inferiours ſhould do whatſoever their Superiours Command, though in their own private O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, it ſeemeth utterly to ſwerve from that which is right.</hi> This Propoſition is by Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> made a Concluſion, to be taken <hi>de fide,</hi> upon the Authority of this Text: The Aſſembling and determination of this firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. The Argument muſt lye thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>If the Spirit of God directed the Apoſtles and Elders at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> in the Controverted Caſes of Circumciſion, Fornication, and things Offered to Idols, and things ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; to meet together, and to make a final determination, in reference to Chriſtians Practice: And it were the Will of God, that all private Chriſtians ſhould do according to their determination, though in their own Opinions it utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſwerved from that which was right: Then it is the will of God, that in all other Matters of Religious Practice, that are Litigious, or Controverted, and of ſuch Quality, as the Superiour judgeth the doing of the things in Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Matters of indifferency, though the Inferiours judge them unlawful: That Superiours ſhould make a final deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and private Chriſtians ſhould do according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations, though their determinations their private Opinions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeem utterly to ſwerve from that which is right.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But the Spirit of God directed the Apoſtles and Elders at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> in the Controverted Caſes of Circumciſion, Fornication, things Offered to Idols, and things ſtrangled; to meet together, and to make a final deciſion: And it was the Will of God, that all Private Chriſtians ſhould Practiſe according to their determinations, though in their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Opinions, they might ſeem utterly to ſwerve from that which is right — <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now, to this Argument, the Anſwer, we ſay, is not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, for neither Propoſition is true, or can be made good, But to ſpeak diſtinclly.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:109403:21"/>§. 11. Firſt, we deny the Conſequence of the <hi>Major,</hi> and that for theſe three Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>There is an apparent difference betwixt Apostles, Men guided by an Infallible Spirit, and any other Superiours unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably more Fallible than they.</hi> They could not err, the beſt Councel now may err.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But Secondly, <hi>there is a vaſt difference betwixt the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes mentioned in the Text, and other Litigious, Controverted Caſes of ſuch Quality,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> mentioneth: So as there is no Arguing, from the one to the other. Thoſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. are by the Apoſtles called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Things neceſſary;</hi> theſe we ſpeak of are confeſſedly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> indifferent, and not neceſſary; either conſidered in themſelves, or in reſpect of any Circumſtance abſtracted from <hi>the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours Precept;</hi> if it be ſaid, That one or two of thoſe things mentioned, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. were but indifferent, <hi>viz. To abſtain from blood, and things ſtrangled,</hi> it is eaſily Anſwered, <hi>That a thing may be neceſſary, either with reſpect to ſome direct pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> (as <hi>Fornication,</hi> and <hi>forbearing eating things firſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Idols,</hi> was. The Apoſt;e, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. Judgeth it a participation at the Idolaters Altar) or with <hi>Reſpect to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,</hi> (and thoſe Antecedaneous to the Superiours Precept) thus abſtaining <hi>from blood,</hi> and <hi>things ſtrangled were,</hi> becauſe of the Jews, who by the Ceremonial Law (the abolition of which they had not yet diſcerned) were forbidden <hi>blood,</hi> and by reaſon of the Converted Gentils eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blood, were much eſtranged from, and hardened againſt the Doctrine of the Goſpel. Therefore the Apoſtle calls them <hi>neceſſary;</hi> not made ſo onely by their Command, but made ſo by this great Circumſtance, the doing of them hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the Glory of God, and his great Deſign then on Foot. Now, to Argue from the Authority of Superiours to make a ſinal deciſion, as to things ſimply neceſſary, as forbidden directly by a Divine Law; Or <hi>Accidentally neceſſary</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their own Nature indifferent) made ſo by ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſcandal, or miſchief, which would plainly follow from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109403:22"/>our not diſceding from our Liberty in ſuch things, eſpecially too where the things required to be forborn, were before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden by a Divine Law. We ſay, from hence to conclude the Authority of Superiours to make final deciſions in other matters, and Command the doing of things never required by God's Law, and confeſſed to be, neither in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves neceſſary, nor in reſpect of any other Circumſtance Antecedaneous to the Superiours Precept, is, (with Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> and his Friends) very wide Arguing, and ſhooting at a great diſtance from the Mark.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> What ſaith this <hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>Reverend Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod; From which if you keep your ſelves, you ſhall do well.</hi> They do not ſay, Theſe things, though indifferent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, you muſt do, becauſe we have made them neceſſary by our command, though you in your private Opinions judge ſome of them utterly unlawful. But we fore-ſee ſome will ſay, That although this Councel uſed a ſoft Expreſſion, yet it manifeſtly followeth, <hi>That if they did not abſtain from theſe things, they ſhould do ill.</hi> We Anſwer, that without Queſtion, if they had not abſtained, they had done ill, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Synod had ſo determined or no. The Councel did but declare What was the Will of God, <hi>i. e. That Men muſt not uſe their Liberty in things indifferent, when the uſe of it will prejudice the Glory of God, in ſo high a concern, as that of Converting Souls.</hi> The matter of the Decree here, was not a thing in that ſtate of the Church, in that place indifferent, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedaneouſly to their Decree, but what was every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Duty, precedent to the Councels determination. The Councel onely inſtructed them in what was the will of God, not make it <hi>neceſſary</hi> by their <hi>Canon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Again, they were things which the Chriſtians could not poſſibly judge <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful;</hi> nothing was required but <hi>abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> either from ſuch things as Gods word at that preſent Obliged them to abſtain from, or had before Obliged the Jews to abſtain from. If the Chriſtians judged themſelves at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to eat of things ſtrangled, and blood, it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible yet, they ſhould judge it ſinful not to eat of them. Now,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109403:22"/>none of us will deny, that in Controverſies of ſuch Quality, where <hi>known neceſſary Duties are Controverted,</hi> or <hi>things neceſſary eminently with reſpect to ſome Circumſtances appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and inavoidable;</hi> but it is the <hi>Will of God,</hi> that the <hi>Church ſhould conſult and declare the Will of God as to them,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians ought to hearken,</hi> and do <hi>according to ſuch their Declaration.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Principally, <hi>becauſe it is the Will of God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Becauſe of the Churches Authority, Adviſing or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding from God;</hi> eſpecially if their required Practice too reacheth no further than a reſtraint of their Liberty, in doing ſome things: not doing things, which their Conſciences judge utterly unlawful. This is enough to ſhew the Vanity of the <hi>Propoſition,</hi> or the Conſequence rather of the Major Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</item>
               </list>
               <p>§. 12. But neither is the <hi>Aſſumption</hi> true. No ſuch thing appeareth from <hi>Acts</hi> 15. That the Chriſtians were bound to do what the Synod required [though in their private Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the things required ſwerved utterly from what was right.] As the things were ſuch, concerning which we before ſaid, the Conſcience of none could ſo dictate. So the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtles knew the mind of God too well, to engage Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to Act contrary to the Opinion of their own Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Nor do we Read, that ever the Authority of this Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod was quoted by the Apoſtle, in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> where he profeſſedly, and largely handles one of theſe Caſes, about things <hi>Offered to Idols.</hi> Doth he tell the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> any ſuch thing, as, <hi>It is unlawful for you now to eat ſuch things. It is indeed in it ſelf a thing indifferent, but your Superiours have decreed you ſhould not eat, therefore now it is neceſſary for you not to eat; the Councel of Hieruſalem made it neceſſary.</hi> No ſuch thing, but he uſeth Arguments proper to Chriſtians Conſciences from the Nature of the thing; The <hi>Scandal,</hi> The <hi>Concern of Gods Glory</hi> in their forbearance.</p>
               <p>§. 13. Thus far we have dealt with the great Champion for the <hi>Blind Obedience</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to whom thoſe unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109403:23"/>as to Conformity, are ſent upon all Occaſions, not onely to perſwade them that <hi>they may,</hi> but that they are <hi>bound to conform,</hi> and it is <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> (and any thing) if they do not; and we hope, however unanſwerable, to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed: Yet the Candid Reader will judge that he is not ſuch <hi>a Lyon,</hi> but he may be taken <hi>by the beard,</hi> and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Inchanted Hand. <hi>Multa videntur &amp; dicuntur quae non ſunt.</hi> We have taken the more pains to Examine this New <hi>Dictate</hi> of his about <hi>The Will of God,</hi> and his Arguments for it, becauſe ſo much hangs upon it, that it being proved <hi>falſe and abſurd,</hi> and his Arguments for it invalid. His <hi>Folio</hi> is of no further uſe, than to inform Men, and when that is done, they ſtill ſtand Obliged to Act <hi>according to the abiding Opinion of their own Conſciences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 24. There is yet another <hi>Father,</hi> whom they much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie upon, but (far more ſparingly quote in this Caſe, and there is Reaſon for it) it is the Reverend Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> (the late Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi>) a Man, who though we know he differed from us, yet we muſt give him his Character. That we have not, nor ever had ſuch another Adverſary. He had <hi>praeparatum pectus</hi> for an Argument; and ſeldom determines a Queſtion but clearly, and diſtinctly. So as though we find him ſomething againſt us, yet we can underſtand him ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the point, and clearly, expreſſing what he ſaith. Let us therefore hear him, and where can we better hear him, than in his Book of <hi>Praelections, concerning the Obligation of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi> There he ſpeaketh not by the by, and collaterally, but purpoſely to the Queſtion, <hi>Praelect.</hi> 6. §. 16 He puts this Queſtion, <hi>What certainty is required in the Mind of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to ſecure him in Conſcience, that he is not bound by the Law of his Superiour?</hi> To which he Anſwereth,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That if the Law be manifeſtly, and notoriouſly unjuſt, the Subject may be ſure he is not bound by it; which is alſo true, if by a Moral certainty he judgeth it ſimply unjuſt, having uſed all diligence to find out the Truth.</hi> This is the Caſe, what needeth any more? But he goes on.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:109403:23"/>2. <hi>If he doth but think the Command unjust, from ſome rooted Error in Judgment, of which he cannot eaſily quit himſelf; The Obligation of the Command abideth, notwithſtanding the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of his Mind, ſo that he ſinneth, if he doth not Obey; but he ſhould ſin in an higher degree, if he did Obey.</hi> Errore illo nondum depoſito, <hi>whiles he thinks it unlawful.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>If a Man doth onely from ſome light Scruple or Objection ſuſpect the Law unjust, he ought to contemn that Scruple and Obey.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Here is now a Man ſpeaks like a Divine, clearly, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly diſtinguiſhing, betwixt a demonſtrative certainty, or a certainty of Faith, and a Moral certainty; betwixt the aſſent of a fixed Conſcience, and of an <hi>Opining Conſcience,</hi> and Scruple, or Suſpition, and determining Chriſtians Duty in all Caſes, and ſo ſolidly, that we believe there is no valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> in <hi>England</hi> but will ſubſcribe what he ſaith: He durſt not tell us, <hi>We muſt believe it the Will of God, we ſhould ſubmit to the ſinal deciſion of Superiours, though it our private Opinion it utterly ſwerveth from that which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> right;</hi> he underſtood Divinity a little better. And this we think was his laſt Reſolve in the Caſe. If his firſt Concluſion reach not an <hi>Opining Conſcience,</hi> which we are ſure it doth (if probable Arguments be oppoſed to Revelation and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations,</hi> for then a <hi>Moral certainty</hi> makes but an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) yet we weare ſure the Second doth. As to both he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines <hi>Acting</hi> unlawful; which is all we contend for.</p>
               <p>§. 15. But there is another paſſage more uſually quoted in this Caſe, in a Sermon which that <hi>Reverend</hi> and <hi>Learned man</hi> hath on <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. which we will conſider, though not half ſo valuable as this.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe but in a Sermon, where he ſpake to it collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And in a Sermon Preached in his Younger Years: But neither can we find any thing there to their purpoſe, for, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving there determined concerning <hi>a Conſcience fully Reſolved about the unlawfulneſs of a thing,</hi> viz. <hi>That a Man cannot
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109403:24"/>without ſin do the thing ſo by his Conſcience judged unlawful.</hi> He cometh, in the next place, to treat of a Mans Duty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a doubting Conſcience (where we deſire the Reader to conſider, that he either comprehendeth the <hi>Opining Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> under the Notion of the <hi>Conſcience fully Reſolved,</hi> as one would think by that paſſage, §. 25. <hi>This is now where the Conſcience apparently inclineth one way; but ſay the Scales hang even,</hi> &amp;c. Or elſe he quite leaps over the <hi>Opining Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> as not ſo much concerned in his Text. §. 25. He manifeſtly ſpeaks not of it, but of ſuch a Conſcience (as he expreſſeth himſelf) <hi>where the Scales hang even, and a Man cannot reſolve which way he ſhould take.</hi> And again, §. 29. Anſwering the <hi>Objection: I cannot do it, it is againſt my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>It is not againſt thy Conſcience, for, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is properly an indifferent motion to either part of a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; when the Mind is held in ſuſpence betwixt two ways, uncertain which to take, when the Scales hang even</hi> (as I ſaid before) <hi>in aequilibro.</hi> This manfieſtly is not an Opining Conſcience, but <hi>perfectè dubia,</hi> a Conſcience which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly doubteth. Now, under ſuch a Complexion of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience as to ſome matter of Practice he determineth,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That if the Liberty of the Agent be determined by a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Power — A Man is bound in Conſcience to do the thing Commanded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a very diſputable point in Matters where the Soul is concerned: but be it ſo or ſo, it nothing concerns us in the preſent Debate. That Conſcience which we are ſpeaking of is not a Conſcience hanging betwixt the two contradictory parts of a Practical Propoſition, but upon Arguments which appear to it very probable, (though not demonſtrative) ſtrongly inclining to judge one part unlawful, and that the part Commanded, and Morally certain of it. The Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, Whether this Man can do it or no, becauſe he is not, as <hi>Hooker</hi> ſaith, <hi>fully and ſettledly perſwaded,</hi> or becauſe, as others ſay it is, <hi>not plainly, and demonſtratively, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently evil, tending to debauch Men in their apprehenſions of the God-head,</hi> &amp;c. To this Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> either ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109403:24"/>or ſpeaks quite contrary; for indeed here the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is <hi>repugnant;</hi> in which Caſe, like a good Proteſtant Divine, he determines quite contrary to our <hi>Neotericks,</hi> §. 29. <hi>That no Repect nor Circumſtance whatſoever can free ſuch an Action from ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 16. We find a late Caſui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſpeaking as honeſtly. It is Mr. <hi>Fulwood</hi> (whom the <hi>Author of Toleration not to be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> declares himſelf ſo much pleaſed with, that he aſſures us, he is much of his Mind) and it is in one of the three Books he is in ſuch Love with, Entituled, <hi>Some neceſſary and ſeaſonable Caſes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 126. though he adviſeth, <hi>That in ſuch Caſes where things are Commanded, which the Inferiour Judgeth unlawful, Men ſhould ſuſpect their private Judgments, and read, and ſearch ſtill yet,</hi> at laſt, (ſaith he) <hi>if the thing required appear to thee ſinful ſtill. Thou art bound to the Peace of thy own Conſcience, Gods Vice-gerent within thee, and thou mayest not Obey.</hi> How come we then to be <hi>Felons de ſe.</hi> and <hi>Sacrilegious?</hi> Stealing our ſelves out of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, when this is plainly the caſe. Nothing could be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more truly, or like a Divine; and it ſpeaks the more honeſty in Mr. <hi>Fulwood,</hi> becauſe in ſaying this he ſpake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf, kicking down all the good Milk, which his <hi>Conformable</hi> Brethren thought he had given in thoſe three Books.</p>
               <p>§. 17. We find another Recent <hi>Doctor,</hi> in a Pamphlet, called <hi>Pulpit Conceptions: Popular deceptions;</hi> nibbling, and but nibbling at this moſt important Queſtion, p. 61. He forms an Objection thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſuppoſe I ſhould Scruple my Obedience, thinking my Superiours impoſitions to be againſt the Command of God: Why, in this caſe I am Obliged to lay aſide my Scruples, and to bring ſuch thoughts into Captivity to the Obedience of Chriſt, who hath commanded me to Obey thoſe that have the Rule over me.</hi> Pulpit Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. p. 61.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:109403:25"/>Right. But had we been any of us at this Doctors Elbow, who thus dictates, we would have told him, <hi>Doctors,</hi> this none will deny you; but they are not <hi>Scruples</hi> that are in our way, but great <hi>Maſſie ſtones,</hi> called <hi>Dialectick Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> yea, almoſt <hi>Mill-ſtones:</hi> that is, we have not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Jealouſie, or Suſpition, or Fear, that the thing m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> unlawful: But we are as ſure or it as we can be of any th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that it is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid in Scripture, nor the Object of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Senſe, nor demonſtrable from certain and neceſſary cauſes. Good <hi>Doctor,</hi> ſpeak to the purpoſe; may we Act againſt the Judgment of our Conſciences, made up from theſe, or no? The Men you deal with in that Boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e many of them Men of great Learning and Reaſon, whoſe Arguments none in in their wits will think you have Anſwered in that Book. What ſhall be done in this caſe, Doctor? Speak to the point. Is there nothing to do, but <hi>up</hi> and <hi>ride</hi> your pace? Where's the <hi>Stirrup?</hi> we ſee the Whip, but we ſee not that. <hi>Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous</hi> Doctor, you know it is a <hi>little ſtone?</hi> a thing without the Foot (much like an <hi>Ipſe dixit</hi> for an Argument to prove an action Lawful) if a Man indeed hath ſuch a thing in his ſhooe vexing his Foot, it is an eaſie thing for him to pull it out, and caſe himſelf, and run preſently. But ſuppoſe a Man hath the <hi>Gout,</hi> or ſome <hi>intrinſick Humour,</hi> which La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth him; is it no more than to ſay, <hi>up, and Run?</hi> Good Doctor, he muſt be cured firſt, I hope. The <hi>Divines</hi> which you have to deal with, have ſuch impediments, <hi>intrinſick, Arguments,</hi> which maketh the unlawfulneſs of the things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired very probable to them. If you will call them <hi>Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> they cannot help that, but they are no more of Kin to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem, than a grain of Sand is to a Mill-ſtone. They are ready <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Argue the Caſe with you at any fair Barr of any Reformed Church in <hi>Europe:</hi> You have their Arguments: Againſt <hi>Set Forms of Prayer to be impoſed upon all Miniſters,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Cottons Diſcourſe againſt Set Forms.</hi> Againſt the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, in Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> his <hi>Freſh Suit?</hi> In the Diſpute <hi>againſt Engliſh Ceremonies,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi>'s Books. Againſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdination,</hi> in <hi>R. A.</hi> his Letter to a Friend, Printed 1661. and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:109403:25"/>
                  <hi>A Serious Review of Presbyters Re-ordination by Biſhops,</hi> Printed about the ſame time. As alſo in <hi>Altare Damaſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> upon the two firſt Heads: Beſides many other Books they could never yet ſee Anſwered. What ſhall theſe Men do? You hear what they ſay; you ſay nothing, but rail at them, and conclude them <hi>peeviſh, wilful, ungovernable,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Anſwering an Argument, but taking it for granted (as a late Triumphant Author) that they think all Lawful, onely Scruple offending their Party. Will you tell them as you do, p. 61, 62, 63. <hi>That Melior est conditio poſſidentis. He that is in poſſeſſion hath the bettter Intereſt, and that he is poſſeſſed of his Right in Commanding, is unqueſtionable; and therefore they are bound, in Conſcience, to ſtand to his Command, till it be evinced that his command is of a thing that is ſinful, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Sphear of his Authority.</hi> Alas! they will preſently grant it you, with this difference. They will tell you, they will not ſay, their Superiour Commands things which are <hi>apparently, and demonſtrably ſinful.</hi> But the things Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded are <hi>to them ſinful,</hi> being ſuch as their Conſciences ſo Judge, and that from Arguments which appear to them highly probable, enough to beget in them a Moral certainty. You gag them at the Preſs, what you can, but they have found times from thence to tell you what thoſe Arguments are; what is their Anſwer? You are a Company of peeviſh, factious, Schiſmatical Fellows. Is this Righteous dealing? Or had not theſe kind of Anſwerers, think you, need of ſome <hi>more Righteouſneſs</hi> than their <hi>own works,</hi> to juſtifie them? They will preſently grant, That the Superiour is poſſeſſed of an unqueſtionable Right to Command in ſuch things, as God by his Word hath not forbidden, either by ſome <hi>particular word,</hi> or by ſome general Law, requiring every one to uſe their Power derived from God, <hi>for good,</hi> for <hi>Edification,</hi> not for <hi>Deſtruction;</hi> to uſe it ſo, as not to <hi>deſtroy Souls, for whom Chriſt dyed.</hi> And to all ſuch Commands, they profeſs themſelves ready to ſtand.</p>
               <p>And further, when you have proved, that either the Word of God, or right Reaſon hath put the Superiour in a <hi>poſſeſſion</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:109403:26"/>of a larger Right than this is. They will tell you, That the <hi>King of Spain</hi> is in a poſſeſſion too of a Right to Command; ſo was Queen <hi>Mary</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> who Commanded ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, ſhe, or her Biſhops, or both; which <hi>Cranmer, Hooper, Ridley, Latimer,</hi> &amp;c. in their Conſciences judged unlawful; how was it <hi>Evinced</hi> (to uſe your term) to thoſe and other good Men, that what theſe their Superiours Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, was unlawful? The <hi>Biſhops</hi> affirmed them Lawful, ſo that (according to the Modern Divinity) the <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> of them could be but the Sufferers private Opinion, and that againſt the Church. Did theſe Men ſin, in not doing the things required? Did they dye as Fools dye? Or did they do their Duty in chuſing to Suffer rather than Act? If the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, why may not others do the ſame? Will you ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe things to the Martyrs were <hi>evinced</hi> unlawful. We ask, how were they evinced? Did they plead Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt: thoſe things, and do not the Non-Conformiſts do ſo now? Had they not a far greater appearance of Scripture for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> in that Text, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> than any can bring for a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> a <hi>Surplis,</hi> &amp;c. Will you ſay, the Scriptures now pleaded, are wreſted, and miſ-underſtood? Would not <hi>Bonner</hi> and <hi>Gardiner</hi> ſay ſo then? Shall the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate now determine betwixt the Biſhops and diſſenters? And had not Queen <hi>Mary</hi> the ſame Right? Or (at leaſt) ſhe and her Parliament? See where you are, Doctor. Who ſhall Judge whether your oppoſite Objections be <hi>Scruples, Doubts,</hi> or <hi>Opinions?</hi> Shall the Supreme Magiſtrate or the Biſhops? Had not Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and her <hi>Biſhops</hi> the ſame Right? And then all thoſe Holy Men dyed, as the Papiſts ſay, as <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traytors,</hi> and thoſe things were all ſuffered in vain. You have no way to avoid this, unleſs you will ſay, Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and her Biſhops were no Superiours; for you know, <hi>Quod convenit alicui quâ tali, convenit omni tali.</hi> But it may be when this <hi>Doctor</hi> writes next, he will think himſelf Obliged to ſpeak ſtrictly, and not confound, a <hi>Doubting, Scrupulous,</hi> an <hi>Opining</hi> Conſcience. Any School-man, or Caſuiſt will ſhew him the difference betwixt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:109403:26"/>§. 18. The laſt we ſhall take Notice of, ſpeaking in this Caſe, is one, who calls himſelf <hi>Ireneus Freeman,</hi> in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe ſtiled by him, <hi>The Reaſonableneſs of Divine Service,</hi> p. 33. he telleth us right. <hi>That there are but a few Actions but are diſputable;</hi> and — <hi>In diſputable Actions, we muſt Obey our Superiours Commands.</hi> This is now right down, that is, <hi>There are very few Actions, but let our own Conſciences ſay what they will to us againſt them, if our Superiours Command us to do them, we muſt do them:</hi> Or ſay <hi>what they will for them, if the Magistrate Command us to forbear them, we muſt forbear them.</hi> In p. 15. Thoſe he had to deal with having ſaid, that it was not clear to them, <hi>That it was Lawful for all Perſons at all times to limit themſelves in Praycr by any ſtinted Forms,</hi> This acute Author roundly tells them.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Lawfulneſs of an Action is not clear to him that doubteth of its Lawfulneſs, not being certain that the Action is Lawful, nor yet certain that it is unlawful. But yet ſuch a Man is bound to do the Action when Commanded by the Magiſtrate. The Reaſon is, Becauſe it is certain the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is to be Obeyed, Commanding Lawful things. But it is uncertain whether the thing be unlawful; it is ſafer to Obey doubtingly, than to diſobey doubtingly.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now, in theſe words, there is either a <hi>Notorious Cheat,</hi> or elſe a Potion of Divinity, which taken down, will bring up all our <hi>Proteſtant Religion:</hi> If there be a Cheat, it lyes in thoſe words, <hi>Doubting,</hi> and <hi>Certain.</hi> A Conſcience may be ſaid to be doubting, either <hi>ſtrictly,</hi> or <hi>largely.</hi> Strictly, Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> tells us what a doubting Conſcience is, when the Mind is pendulous, the Scales hang even: a Man hath as much to ſay for the Lawfulneſs of an Action, as for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs. Largely, One that is meerly Jealous, Scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, or Suſpitious of an Action, may be ſaid to doubt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. One that is not fully perſwaded a thing is unlawful, but upon Arguments, which he judgeth very probable, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth it unlawful. Again, a Man may be certain of a thing, by a <hi>certainty of Faith,</hi> believing a <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> or by a <hi>certainty of Senſe,</hi> or ariſing from <hi>Demonſtration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:109403:27"/>2. A Man may be <hi>Morally certain,</hi> and of moſt things we have no other certainty than this latter. If this Author had not deſigned to cheat his Reader, he would have ſpoken di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly (as we ſhewed Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> did) when he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of <hi>Doubting,</hi> he muſt either ſay nothing to the purpoſe, for he knows his Adverſaries have given him Arguments, which appear to them very probable why they Judge the things required unlawful. Or elſe he muſt mean, that if a Man hath any <hi>doubt,</hi> and be not <hi>fully perſwaded,</hi> that the Action is unlawful, though he hath never ſo many Arguments, which make it appear to him probably ſuch: Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, he is bound to do the thing. Now, if this be his Sence, he ſaith that which is not to be made good by any but Mr. <hi>Hooker's</hi> Principles, before ſpoken to, and that which I will think never any Proteſtant ſpake before him. For his Rule of <hi>Tene certum, relinque incertum;</hi> beſides that, it muſt be underſtood of the two parts of the ſame Propoſition, not of two diſtinct Propoſitions (as he wrings it.) By his leave <hi>that is not uncertain,</hi> of which we <hi>are Morally certain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor 3. Is it certain, or can be to any Soul, either by <hi>Faith,</hi> or <hi>Mathematically,</hi> or <hi>Morally. That the Superiour is in all things to be Obeyed:</hi> Nay, the contrary is certain. Nor is it certain that he is to be Obeyed in things, which <hi>the Inferiour,</hi> upon Arguments which he judgeth very probable, <hi>Judgeth unlawful for him to do.</hi> For his confounding the Notions of <hi>Diſputable, and uncertain,</hi> it is ridiculous; for if all things <hi>diſputable</hi> be therefore <hi>uncertain,</hi> becauſe they are diſputed, and that by ſome Learned Men too, whether the particular Soul, diſpute them or no. There's hardly an Article of our Faith will be left us <hi>certain,</hi> or indeed any thing elſe but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, <hi>That we muſt Obey our Superiours.</hi> In the mean time, Reader, Obſerve whither theſe Modern Caſuiſts are dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>There are few Actions</hi> (he might have added Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions too) <hi>that are not Diſputable,</hi> Freeman, p. 33.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In Diſputable Actions we muſt Obey Superiours Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> ibid. p. 15.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:109403:27"/>3. Yea, we muſt Obey, though we doubt, <hi>i. e.</hi> though upon Arguments which to us appear very probable; we think the things unlawful to be done, becauſe <hi>it is certain</hi> (ſaith <hi>Freeman</hi>) <hi>That Superiours are to be Obeyed in things Lawful, and in diſputable things it is uncertain that what is required is unlawful.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Ergo. <hi>There are very few Actions, but if we be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded this or that part, let our Conſciences ſay what they will, we muſt do as we are commanded.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>§. 19. Theſe now are Doctrines not fit to be openly, and plainly aſſerted in this Noon-day of Truth. Therefore the particular Judgments of Private Perſons, Founded on Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which to them ſeem very probable, and inferr a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral certainty, muſt be confounded with the Notions of <hi>Doubts, Scruples, Fears, Jealouſies.</hi> Let this Doctrine obtain a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and let the World Judge, if the <hi>exploded, brutiſh, odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Blind Obedience</hi> (the Pillar, and <hi>Baſis of Popery</hi>) be not by ſlight of hand eſtabliſhed. The Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of this Doctrine, if true, would be this, <hi>That Men need no more look to Scripture, to ſee whether an Action were Lawful or no, but look upon it as the Will of God; to believe as the Church believeth, and do as their Superiours command, without any regard to the command of God.</hi> Of this, more anon.</p>
               <p>§. 20. The Advantage of this Doctrine (pretended) is <hi>Peace,</hi> by which they can mean no more, than an outward Harmony in Action.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſtretching the bounds of Morality.</hi> For, if two ſucceſſive Superiours Command me the two contradictory parts of the ſame Propoſition: One Commands me to go to Church: Another, to tarry at home, and I am bound to Obey in things diſputable; it muſt follow, that all things in the World that are diſputable, are <hi>indifferent.</hi> Now, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as Mr. <hi>Freeman</hi> ſaith) <hi>few actions not Diſputable.</hi> It muſt follow, that there are few <hi>Practical Propoſitions,</hi> but a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109403:28"/>Man, as to them may do what he liſt, take what part he pleaſeth; ſo all things ſhall become Lawful. But now the woful diſ-advantage of it, is, that he who practiſeth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe Principles.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Shall be ſure to have no Peace in his Conſcience, but a continual regret within himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>He will be at last damned. For</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>he that doubteth, is damned if he eateth,</hi> Rom. 14. Except ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body can prove what hath been impudently enough ſaid, <hi>That Superiours muſt another day anſwer to God for all the ſinful actions which their Inferiours have done at their command,</hi> (a Doctrine no Superiour hath cauſe to thank them for.) Nor is there any way to avoid the firſt, unleſs it were poſſible for Men to perſwade themſelves, as Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> would have them, <hi>That it is the Will of God, that in Litigious and controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted caſes of ſuch Quality, Men ſhould ſubmit to the judgment of final deciſion; though in their private Opinions they Judge it ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to ſwerve from that which is right;</hi> as to which we have ſaid enough. We therefore ſtick to the Proteſtant Doctrine,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is not Lawful, under any circumſtance of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to act againſt an Opining Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:109403:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The Queſtion ſtated; It is proved, that it is not Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Act contrary to the Opinion of a Mans parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Conſcience, by five Arguments; becauſe the particular Conſcience is the Proximate Rule of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, granted by all Divines. Becauſe of that Text, <hi>Rom. 14.23.</hi> Becauſe it Subjects a Man to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Terrors of Conſcience. The contrary Principle over-throws the Natural Order of the Souls Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and plucks up a great Pillar of the Proteſtant Religion, and would make the Scriptures and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative Books of little <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe but to Torment Men.</head>
               <p>§. 1. WE come now to aſſert our <hi>Propoſition, That it is not Lawful for any Perſon to act againſt an Opining Conſcience,</hi> i. e. (as we have largely opened). That, ſuppoſing a Perſon, though he hath not demonſtrative Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, to prove this or that unlawful, which he is required to do: Yet if he hath formed up a particular Judgment of Conſcience, from Arguments, which ſeem to him <hi>very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,</hi> ſo as he cannot Anſwer them, nor reſt ſatisfied in the Anſwers of others, while he ſo judgeth, it is ſin and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in him, eſpecially in Matters which concern the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, to do that Action, however required of him. This we ſhall make good by ſeveral Arguments.</p>
               <p>§. 2.1. <hi>To ſwerve from what God hath made the Proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Rule of our actions, is ſinful. But to act contrary to the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our own Conſciences, is to ſwerve from what God bath made the Proximate Rule of our Actions</hi> — Therefore it is ſinful. The <hi>Major</hi> can with no Modeſty be denyed; for, what is ſin, but a Tranſgreſſion of, or <hi>deviation from the Rule of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109403:29"/>our actions?</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> is as Evident. It is granted by <hi>all Divines</hi> we have met with, both <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> that the <hi>Practical Conſcience</hi> is the Proximate Rule of our Actions; nor did we ever meet with it denyed by any Learned Man. And indeed it muſt be ſo; For, That <hi>Gods Word and Law</hi> is the <hi>Remote Rule,</hi> muſt be owned. Now, we would ask how we ſhall know what <hi>the Will of God in his Word is,</hi> but by the Judgment of our <hi>particular conſciences at laſt;</hi> be the Will of God in it ſelf what it will: The Will of God to us muſt be Interpreted as to Practiſe by our own <hi>Judgments and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions.</hi> Hence Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> ſaith well, that he who acteth againſt his Conſcience, <hi>Interpretatively acts againſt the Will of God.</hi> And <hi>Filiucius</hi> ſaith right; ſuch Actions declare, that Men chuſe, and love ſin: For ſo far as they know what is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, they do ſin; and if they miſs of ſinning in their Actions, it is but <hi>as the blind Man hits the Crow,</hi> there's no thank to them; out of choyce they ſin: <hi>It is involuntarily,</hi> if they do that which is right. No Action materially good, can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be ſo formally, if done contrary to the Judgment of our Conſcience; becauſe it is impoſſible it ſhould have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the Will, whiles the Practical Conſcience faith it ought not be done. The <hi>Will</hi> cannot <hi>will</hi> what it judgeth evil, it may indeed be miſ-guided by the Underſtanding, but it cannot will evil, <hi>ſub ratione mali;</hi> and ſo conſequentially cannot <hi>will</hi> what the Conſcience telleth the Man he ought not to do. So as indeed it is but a Natural Principle, <hi>That the Practical Conſcience is, and muſt be the Proximate Rule of our actions. Filiucius</hi> ſaith right, that the Law of God, and the Law of Nature reſpecteth our Actions as they are free, which they cannot be, unleſs they proceed <hi>a Principio cognoſcente,</hi> from a knowing Principle within our ſelves. We proceed to a ſecond Argument.</p>
               <p>§. 3. <hi>That Principle, which allowed perverteth the whole Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Nature in the operations of a Reaſonable ſoul, muſt be falſe. But this opinion, That it is Lawful for us to act contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to what appears to us Lawful, from probable arguments,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:109403:29"/>perverteth the whole Order of Nature in the Operations of a Reaſonable Soul—Ergo.</hi> The Major needeth no proof to any who will believe, that it is not the Will of God, a Man ſhould be Metamorphoſed into a Beaſt. So that all our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs muſt be to prove the <hi>Minor.</hi> To which purpoſe let us but take a view of the Nobleſt Empire in the World, I mean, that of Reaſon in Man; and Obſerveth the Order which God hath (by the Law of Nature preſcribed) by which Reaſon, ſitting as a Queen, ſhould Rule there.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Will</hi> is the great <hi>Miniſter</hi> in this State, the great wheel, which by its imperate Acts moveth the whole Man. The Object of it is <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil;</hi> about theſe two it is Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, chuſing the former, refuſing the latter, and then Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all the Inferiour Faculties of the Soul, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Body, to move according to its Judgment and Choice. The <hi>Philopſoher</hi> telleth us, <hi>The Will is blind,</hi> and that its work is onely to keep its Seat, and Judge, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. The Underſtanding ſerves it with the Notion of things that takes cogniſance of them, diſcerns, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents them as true, or falſe; whether reference to Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Practice. The Underſtanding in its work is ſerved by the <hi>Interior</hi> and <hi>exterior Senſes.</hi> So then this is the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Ceaſonable Soul in Man, whereas all Objects are either <hi>Senſible, Rational,</hi> or <hi>Spiritual.</hi> The exterior Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the <hi>Eye</hi> and <hi>Ear,</hi> &amp;c. bring Intelligence of ſenſible Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. The <hi>Fancy, Memory,</hi> and <hi>Imaginative Power</hi> bring Intelligence of Objects proper to their Sphear. The Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding takes notice of all Propoſitions thus brought in to it, diſcerneth them, and judgeth concerning them, whether they be true or falſe according to Principles of <hi>Senſe, Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Revelation,</hi> according to the variety of the Matter; upon this the Will maketh its choice. Thoſe which the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding diſcerneth <hi>true</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> it willeth and chuſeth; what it diſcerns falſe and evil, it refuſeth, nillete, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecteth; and accordingly Commandeth the Soul to believe, or not believe; to love, or hate; to deſire, or fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e from what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Underſtanding diſcerneth, and judgeth evil and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109403:30"/>noxious. Here now is the Government of a Reaſonable Soul. Now, let us Obſerve how guilty the Principle we op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Sedition</hi> againſt this <hi>Noble Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Soul</hi> inſtituted in it by God himſelf. We cannot make a better Judgment, than by putting a particular caſe. Suppoſe this the Propoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is, or it is not Lawful for Perſons once Ordained to be re-ordained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Caſe now is to be Judged in the Court of Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Senſes bring</hi> in this Propoſition; as what they have ſome where <hi>ſeen</hi> or <hi>heard</hi> to be brought into Practice. Upon this the Court of the Reaſonable Underſtanding taketh cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance of it. The Underſtanding diſcerns it a Propoſition relating to <hi>Inſtituted Worſhip,</hi> and that the Truth concerning it, is to be determined, not from <hi>Principles of Senſe,</hi> or <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Natural Reaſon,</hi> but from <hi>Scripture and Reaſon</hi> working upon things Revealed, and <hi>comparing things Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual with Spiritual.</hi> The Eye is therefore employed to Read what can be. The <hi>Ear</hi> to hear on all ſides what is ſpoken about it. The <hi>Fancy</hi> or Imagination is alſo ſet on work to find out <hi>Mediums</hi> to prove the one part or other, and ſo the thing cometh with all theſe helps to be Diſcourſed by the ſoul within it ſelf. Then the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> diſcerneth and judgeth which part of the Propoſition is true, and conſequently, fit to be Practiſed; which is falſe, and fit to be rejected. It either concludes one part <hi>Demonſtratively, and certainly falſe,</hi> or <hi>probably, and in all likelihood falſe;</hi> or elſe it hangs in <hi>equilibrio,</hi> not knowing what to determine. In the preſent Caſe we ſuppoſe the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> to bring in its report in this Senſe.</p>
               <p>As to this Practical Queſtion, <hi>Whether it be Lawful for them, who by Miniſters have been Ordained and made Miniſters, to be re-ordained, and made, firſt, Deacons, then Prieſts, by Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have done my beſt to try the Truth or Falſhood of either part. The <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Ears</hi> have given me an account of what they have ſeen in any Books, or heard from any Diſcourſes of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109403:30"/>Learned Men about it. The <hi>Fancy</hi> hath alſo been employed to weigh, and conſider Propoſitions to conſider Arguments brought by others on one ſide, and the other; and deviſe <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums</hi> for one part, and for the other. Now, upon my ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Judgment of the thing from weighing Arguments on all ſides, it is not demonſtratively certain, that this Propoſition is falſe. <hi>That Perſons once Ordained, may not be re-ordained,</hi> and that a <hi>Submiſſion to</hi> ſuch a re-ordination would be ſinful: But it doth appear to me very probably ſo; I cannot Anſwer the Arguments which I have thought on, or others have brought to prove it ſo; and though I dare not arrogate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility to my ſelf, and determine the Arguments I have for the Negative unanſwerable; yet I can find no Anſwer I can acquieſce in, and ſo far as I can judge, it is ſinful; and will certainly iſſue in <hi>horror of Conſcience,</hi> or <hi>Eternal Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or both, without pardoning Mercy. Now, the buſineſs is ripe for the <hi>Will's</hi> Election. What ſhall the <hi>Will do?</hi> Shall it, can it (notwithſtanding this) chuſe the thing, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the ſoul, <hi>to will, deſire, embrace it,</hi> or the <hi>outward Man</hi> to do it, becauſe it is Commanded. If this be not to turn a Man into a Beaſt, to turn the Rational ſoul out of doors, and ſet a Man with his heels upward, and to pervert the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Order of the Souls Operations, we know not what is?</p>
               <p>§. 4. Willany ſay, the Caſe is here partially repreſented, becauſe under the Circumſtance of <hi>Superiours Command.</hi> The Underſtanding hath alſo a report to bring in about that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>That it is by Divine Precept neceſſary to Obey Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours.</hi> We Anſwer, if the Propoſition be laid down ſo Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, the Underſtanding muſt either <hi>Deny it,</hi> or <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> about it. It muſt therefore be onely laid down thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In all Lawful things it is neceſſary to obey Superiours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, it hinders not, for this is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> this is the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, whether the thing be Lawful or no: The Soul judgeth otherwiſe. Now, we would gladly know of our Modern Caſuiſts, <hi>Whether the Law of Nature having obliged the Will
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:109403:31"/>to move According to the dictate of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding, is be poſſible that a rational Soul without preſumptuous ſinning, and offering violence to the very Law and Principles of Humane Nature, ſhould, will, chuſe, command, or allow a thing ſo repreſented to it as before, probably unlawful.</hi> What we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not apprehend good, I hope we cannot will it, for this were to will evil under the Notion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evil (a thing Naturally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.) Now, how ſhall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> judge that good (being to take all its Evidence from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>llect) which the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judgeth falſe, and naught? Will any one ſay, that it is poſſible that from extrinſecal Arguments (ſuch as the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Teſtimony of Men, the Will and Command of Superiours) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it may judge that true and good, which from intrinſecal Arguments, it judgeth falſe and naught. This is indeed the <hi>Jeſuites Doctrine.</hi> (Yet they will not allow a Superiours <hi>merum imperium,</hi> a ſufficient Topick in the caſe) but as was ſaid before, it is juſtly abominated by all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, of what ſort, ſize, or perſwaſion ſoever.</p>
               <p>§. 5. <hi>Exabundanti,</hi> if any will be ſo vain, as to ſay, the Soul hath warrant enough to judge the thing <hi>probably Lawful,</hi> becauſe <hi>Superiours bave Commanded it;</hi> when in the mean time from Arguments appearing to it very probable, it judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſinful and unlawful. We would gladly know, from what Principles it ſhould form ſuch a Judgment; the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple muſt be one of theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Either theſe <hi>Superiours are Infallible,</hi> ſo am <hi>not I in the Exerciſe of my Reaſon.</hi> So inded the <hi>Papiſts</hi> hold, as to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſo may be juſtified in their perverſe Judgments in this caſe from that Maxime, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Granting one abſurdity, a thouſand will follow: But all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants reſerve Infallibility from him, who is Truth it ſelf, and deny it to any Creature.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It muſt therefore be this Principle: <hi>Though Superiours be fallible, yet it is better their Judgments</hi> (though in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them there be a danger of a troubled Conſcience, and eternal damnation) <hi>than my own.</hi> But is it poſſible an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109403:31"/>Rational Soul ſhould ſo Judge? This being neither ſenſibly, not rationally demonſtrable: It is impoſſible that the Soul ſhould apprehend any ſuch thing but upon <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> It muſt teerefore (as <hi>Hooker</hi> ſaith) appear to be <hi>The will of God;</hi> and to that (as to the higheſt Reaſon) (if it can be ſhewed) Reaſon Sanctified and Regulated by Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will ſubmit. Aut alas! who ſhall ſhew us any ſuch Text? <hi>Ante retro Simoeis ſtuet,</hi> &amp;c. Will they urge <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> and other Texts of the like import. We allow the Scripture, we ſay, the matter to be our Duty, but we ſay, it muſt be in things <hi>which do not appear to us ſinful and wicked</hi> (this were to ſet up ſome higher than the higheſt?) Otherwiſe the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. much erred, not onely in their Practice, but in their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple too there laid down, <hi>It is better to obey God than Man:</hi> In vain had they ſaid that, if every Obedience to Man as a Superiour were, <hi>co nomine,</hi> Obedience to God, will any ſay? But <hi>this was where a Magiſtrate Commanded a thing unlawful.</hi> How did that appear, <hi>but by the dictate of their Conſciences?</hi> It indeed now doth otherwiſe appear to us, becauſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo repreſents it ſince written; but how did it appear to them otherwiſe? Why might not the Magiſtrate have then told them, as ſome now Interpret that revealed will of God to us. <hi>He that doubteth, is damned, if he eateth;</hi> that is, (except his Superiour Commands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m to eat.) And why might not <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> have told the three Children, It is true, God had forbidden them to Worſhip Graven Images, but it muſt be underſtood, <hi>excegt the Magiſtrate Commanded them ſo to do:</hi> But this Objection is too ridiculous to Anſwer further. Let this be enough for our Second Argument.</p>
               <p>§. 5. We proceed to a <hi>Third Argument,</hi> which we form thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For any Perſon to do that in the doing of which he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have any quiet, and peace in his own Conſcience, is</hi> ſinful <hi>and</hi> wicked.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But for a Man to Act (under any Circumſtance) contrary
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109403:32"/>to the Opinion of his own Conſcience, is to do that, in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which he can never have any quiet, and Peace in his own Conſcience.</hi> — Ergo.</p>
               <p>We are much at loſs to fancy which Propoſition any can be hardy enough to deny. Will any deny the <hi>Major?</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Charity begins at home; and every Man, in the firſt place, is bound to keep <hi>Quiet</hi> within himſelf, if he can. <hi>Thou art bound to the Peace of thy own Conſcience. Thou canſt not Obey</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Fulwood,</hi> in the place before cited) a very remarkable Sentence for the Author of the <hi>Doctrine of Schiſm,</hi> to think upon profeſſing ſo much oneneſs of mind with Mr. <hi>Fulwood,</hi> in that Book) and certainly, he is the greateſt Self-deſtroyer in the World, that doth not firſt look in his Actions, to ſecure the Peace of his Conſcience. Next, throwing a Man's ſelf into Hell, the greateſt miſchief he can do himſelf, is to ſet his Conſcience upon a continual belch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Face.</p>
               <p>§. 6. For the <hi>Minor:</hi> It is as plain, for he muſt have a dull, a very dull and lazy Conſcience, that will let him Act contrary to its Judgment, and yet be quiet, and not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually tell him, thou ſubjecteſt thy ſelf to the wrath of God, thou ſinneſt wilfully, preſumptuouſly; and there is nothing remains for thee, but either a quick Repentance, a ſorrow for what thou haſt done, and a leaving off to do it any more; or a certain dreadful looking for of Divine and fiery Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>§. 7. Will any ſay, why ſhould not a Man's Conſcience be as unquiet while a man contrary to the Command of God for Obeying Superiours, doth not Obey them? The Anſwer is eaſie. No Law of God Obligeth a man to Obey Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours in things which he verily believeth are unlawful; about other things we have no Diſpute. This Argument is ſo Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as it needeth not more words. We therefore proceed to a fourth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:109403:32"/>§. 8. <hi>He that doubteth is damned, if he eateth; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not of Faith, is ſin,</hi> Rom. 14.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But he who doth that, which upon probable Arguments he verily believeth unlawful; doubteth, and yet actethnd acteth not of Faith.</hi> — <hi>ergo he ſinneth, is damned,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Propoſition</hi> is the Apoſtles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. therefore not to be denyed; but yet we find ſome, who will not allow it a Propoſition of immutable Truth, but with ſome Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. That is (as they expound themſelves) if the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be <hi>ſui juris, at Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Perfectly in his own Power,</hi> not required to do the thing, by the Command of his Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, of the Lawfulneſs of which he doubteth: But (ſay they) if the Superiour Commandeth, then he who doth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing, (though he doubteth of the Lawfulneſs of it) runneth no guilt, no hazard of <hi>Damnation.</hi> Now, we would fain believe this if we could, for it would eaſe us of many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing thoughts, but we cannot, for theſe Reaſons, amongſt others.</p>
               <p>§. 9. Firſt, becauſe <hi>what the Apoſtle ſaith, ſeemeth to us but to be according to the Law, and Order of Nature in a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Soul.</hi> That the Underſtanding ſhould firſt repreſent that as true, and good, and therefore <hi>Eligible,</hi> which the Will ſhould chuſe.</p>
               <p>§. 10. Becauſe <hi>it ſeemeth to us poſſible by admitting their Interpretation to elude the whole Law of God, and make any thing Lawful.</hi> For what Reaſon can there be, why what God ſaith in one place, ſhould be underſtood with that limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and not what he ſaith in another? Why may we not <hi>Venerate Images, Go to Maſs, Pray for the Dead, Prophane the Sabbath, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe Oyl, Spittle, Cream, &amp;c. in Baptiſm,</hi> if the Superiour Commandeth, as well as <hi>wear a Surplis,</hi> uſe <hi>the Croſs in Baptiſm, &amp;c.</hi> Doth any one doubt whether theſe things be Lawful or no, or upon probable Arguments, believe the contrary? And is he reſtrained by this Text? Not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109403:33"/>at all by this Interpretation; if Superiours Command theſe, or any of theſe things, will any ſay, <hi>That this Text ſpeaks of things onely in their own Nature indifferent?</hi> We ask, who ſhall Judge what thoſe things are? Shall the Superiour? If ſo, what we ſaid, holdeth; for it is not to be preſumed, he would Command them, if he judgeth them ſinful. Shall the Inferiour? He Judgeth them from probable Arguments Unlawful.</p>
               <p>§. 11. Thirdly, Becauſe (whatſoever ſome Modern Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors ſay) <hi>We ſee no Scripture Tranſlating the guilt of any Perſonal Action of ours to our Superiours, which in Reaſon we ſhould find, if his Command would Juſtifie us, in doing any thing we judge wicked.</hi> Eſpecially conſidering, that whether we Judge it right or no, it may in it ſelf be ſinful, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we had need have our Souls ſecured, as to the guilt of it. We think, with the Apoſtle, <hi>that Sin is an Anomie;</hi> a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law, by Omiſſion, or Commiſſion, or Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity, how we believe, that there is an inſeparable guilt which he cleaves to every <hi>Omiſsion</hi> or <hi>Oblique Action:</hi> every ſin bindeth over the <hi>Doer</hi> or <hi>Omitter</hi> to an <hi>Eternal death:</hi> and want one Scripture to prove, that the ſin, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Obliquity of an Inferiour Action, ſhould be Tranſlated to the Superiour, and ſet upon his ſcore: Thus while ſome deny Chriſts <hi>imputed Righteouſneſs,</hi> they have deviſed a new Doctrine of <hi>Imputed guilt</hi> to the Magiſtrate or Superiour; a Doctrine which no Superiour will thank them for, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth the weight of Divine wrath for ſin. We have heretofore heard, that Superiours may make themſelves guilty of ſin, by Commanding others to ſin: But that the guilt of the <hi>Inferiours Perſonal Action,</hi> ſhould alſo be Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him, and that not to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but to the Superiour, is a Novel, idle Fancy, a brutiſh, and irrational, as well as unſcriptural figment, and ſuch a one, as if admitted, would make the <hi>Crowns of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Mitres of Biſhops</hi> not worth taking up in the Streets. Let God therefore be true, and theſe New Diviners all Lyars; God hath ſaid, <hi>That Soul that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:109403:33"/>ſins, ſhall dye,</hi> and that <hi>every Soul</hi> ſhall <hi>bear its own Iniquity;</hi> and Iniquity that muſt be (if St. <hi>John</hi> deſcribes ſin right) whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is a Tranſgreſſion of the Divine Law.</p>
               <p>§.12. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We cannot admit of this Interpretation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of what followeth in the Apoſtle, <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin.</hi> By Faith, ſaith Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> in his Sermon on <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. is meant, <q>
                     <hi>A Certain perſwaſion of the Mind, that what we do, may Lawfully be done; that</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Action is done by us, either directly contrary to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Verdict of our own Conſiciences, or, at leaſt, doubting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and before we are in ſome competent meaſure aſſured that we may Lawfully do it; that is it which St.</hi> Paul <hi>here denyeth to be of Faith, and of which he pronounceth ſo peremptorily, that it is (eo nomine) ſin.</hi>
                  </q> Now, we are ſure, that he who doth a thing at the Command of others, which ſeemeth to him (from probable Arguments) unlawful, cannot, in this ſence, do it <hi>of Faith, i. e.</hi> with no competent perſwaſion of the Lawfulneſs of it, with no certainty, either <hi>Supernatural, Mathematical,</hi> or <hi>Moral.</hi> The Vanity therefore of this limitation being diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we hope the Propoſition will ſtand good.</p>
               <p>§. 13. For the <hi>Minor,</hi> he who denyeth it, muſt ſay, <hi>That he who Opineth doth not doubt,</hi> which indeed we think ſtrictly he doth not; for he hath, as we ſaid, a <hi>Moral certainty,</hi> but that doth but raiſe the Argument to <hi>à fortiori:</hi> If he, whoſe Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is pendulous, and who hangeth in <hi>Equilibrio,</hi> is damned if he doth the thing, of the Lawfulneſs of which he doubteth; then is he much more <hi>damned,</hi> who doth verily think the thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, and yet will do it. But in the largeſt Notion, Opining is a <hi>Species of doubting;</hi> and if that Text of the Apoſtle be true, of <hi>Doubting,</hi> in any ſenſe, it muſt be in that ſenſe, which is of all, the higheſt. We are able to diſcern no chink, at which our Adverſaries may creep out from the Priſon of this Argument, but ſhall leave it, attending to any thing they ſhall any of them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after offer in Anſwer to it.</p>
               <p>§. 14. Our next Argument ſhall be this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Principle which deſtroyeth the Pillar and Foundation of the Proteſtant Religion, is not to be granted by thoſe who own that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to aſſert it Lawful under any Circumſtance, to Act contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:109403:34"/>to the Opinion of a Mans own Conſcience, deſtroyeth the Pillar and Foundation of the Proteſtant Religion</hi>— Ergo.</p>
               <p>We confeſs this is but <hi>Argumentum ad homines,</hi> and concerns not thoſe whoſe buſineſs is to oppoſe, and Root up the Religion of Proteſtants; but we are ſpeaking to <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who cannot deny the Propoſition.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Aſſumption,</hi> all that we have to do, is to prove that the Aſſerting of this Principle, deſtroyeth, at leaſt, one of the Foundations of the Proteſtant Religion, as it ſtands diſting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>d from <hi>Popery.</hi> This is that, which Divines call <hi>The Judgment of Private and Practical Diſcretion.</hi> Divines ſay, there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Judgment concerning Propoſitions of Truth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is <hi>Authoritative,</hi> or <hi>Nomothetick.</hi> This belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onely to God; all the Men in the World, all their Opinions and Arguments cannot add <hi>a Cubit to the ſtature of Truth,</hi> nor make an <hi>hair of its</hi> Head either <hi>white or black.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Second is <hi>Miniſterial,</hi> and <hi>Declarative.</hi> This belongs to the Church (in the Scriptural Notion of it.) The Apoſtle therefore calls her <hi>the Pillar and ground of Truth:</hi> She keeps the Sacred Records, and when there is a doubt about any portion of them, Miniſterially declareth what is the Truth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third Divines call, The Judgment of <hi>Private and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Diſcretion.</hi> This, Proteſtants ſay, belongs to every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtian, who, by his own Conſcience, (uſing the beſt means firſt which he can for the Information of it) is to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine (as to his own belief and Practice, what is true, and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. And indeed here lyes the great difference betwixt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Protestants.</hi> The Papiſts will not allow the Private Chriſtian to Judge of Truth with reference to his own Practice, but Obligeth People <hi>To believe as the Church believeth,</hi> and defendeth <hi>Blind Obedience</hi> to Superiours as Chriſtians Duty. They make it Lawful for Men, contrary to their own Judgment, and the Dictate of their Conſcience from intrinſick Arguments, to Practice according to the Opinion of one or more Doctors, and neceſſary to Obey all the Decrees of the <hi>Popes,</hi> and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Superiours, if things be not <hi>apparently</hi> and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively unlawful. It may be one <hi>Adrianus</hi> or another, or two may enter their diſſent to this Brutiſh Doctrine, but they do ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally agree it, and this is <hi>Fons &amp; Origo mali.</hi> The very firſt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109403:34"/>thing to be taught their Proſilytes, (as ſilence was in the School of <hi>Pythagoras.</hi>) Hence their <hi>vernacular Bibles</hi> are burnt, and all their other Doctrines are eaſily ſwallowed. The neceſſity of an Infallible Judge is Concluded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 15. On the other ſide it is eſſential to a Proteſtant to be free and in Bondage to no Man, nor as to his Practice to be guided by any but God alone, and his own Conſcience, and his Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Commanding him what his own Conſcience firſt perſwades him to be neceſſary, or, at leaſt, Lawful. He who denyeth this, and pretendeth to hate <hi>Popery,</hi> doth but <hi>abhor Idols,</hi> and <hi>commit Sacriledge.</hi> Nay, he doth indeed but deny that in words, which he owneth, chuſeth, and preferreth; nor is it poſſible, there ſhould be greater Factors for Popery in any place, than thoſe that perſwade Men, that it is Lawful for them under what Circumſtances they can Imagine to Act contrary <hi>to the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> of their own Conſcience, and do what (from which to them ſeem very probable) ſeems <hi>utterly to ſwerve from that which is right,</hi> (to uſe Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s Phraſe.)</p>
               <p>§. 16. Now, let any pluck up this Flood-gate of <hi>Private and Practical Diſcretion,</hi> and tell us what ſhould hinder moſt of the abſurd Doctrines of Popery coming in upon us like an <hi>overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Flood,</hi> if ever we ſhould be ſo miſerable (which is not a thing impoſſible) as in Future Ages, to have a Superiour that ſhall Command the receiving of them, or Practice according to them. As to the falſhood of moſt of them, we have but a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral certainty,</hi> at leaſt, our perſwaſion muſt be Judged no more according to the <hi>Modern Divinity;</hi> for how can we be Infallibly, and demonſtratively certain in things, as to which ſo great a part of the World is of another mind, and ſo many ſuch Learned Men, as <hi>Bellarmine, Stapleton,</hi> and an hundred more, who diſſent from us? Beſides, as we ſhewed before, we are told, that in <hi>Diſputable</hi> things, we can have but an <hi>Opinion</hi> of one part. And this we take to be a <hi>Meditation</hi> worthy of thoſe <hi>Honourable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> amongſt the <hi>Nobility and Gentry of England,</hi> who have ſhewed their Zeal ſo much of late againſt that <hi>Religious</hi> Pagean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Rome.</hi> If any doubt whether Chriſtians have ſuch a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge given them by God, as this of <hi>Private</hi> and <hi>Practical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion;</hi> let them conſider thoſe Texts, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1. uſually quoted for it; and but Read what Biſhop <hi>Davenant,</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:109403:35"/>in his moſt Learned Treatiſe, <hi>De Judice &amp; Normâ fidei,</hi> and all other Proteſtant Writers have ſaid for it. Whoever plucks up this Hedge, we underſtand not if he doth not feel the <hi>Romiſh Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> quickly biting him by the heel; and we cannot but think that Man will be <hi>Curſed,</hi> that goes about to remove this <hi>Land-mark</hi> of all Proteſtants; and cry out to our Superiours, in the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 22.28. <hi>Remove not the Ancient Land-mark, which our Fathers have ſet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 17. We might further add, that the admiſſion of this <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd</hi> and <hi>brutiſh</hi> principle, that if a thing be not <hi>apparently</hi> and <hi>demonſtratively ſinful,</hi> it is Lawful for Men to Act <hi>contrary to the Opinion of their own Conſiciences,</hi> repreſenting it to them (from Arguments, which ſeem to them very probable) unlawful: All Books of Topicks, as to Matters of practice, all Argumentative Books in Divinity would be of no Uſe at all, but noxious, and miſchievous rather: Yea, the Holy Scriptures themſelves would be of very little or no uſe for the uſe of Argumentative Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, in any Science or Diſcipline is to make a propoſition ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Demonſtrative,</hi> or <hi>Probable</hi> to us. Yea, this is the uſe of the Holy Scriptures, as they inform us of Truth. Things are Demonſtrable to us upon the Evidence of <hi>Revelation, Senſe,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> (indeed the firſt is improper, for the certainty ariſing from Divine Revelation, is called <hi>Faith,</hi> not Demonſtration, or Demonſtrative certainty, but it is <hi>quiddam majus,</hi> what is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to us upon a <hi>certainty of Faith,</hi> or Demonſtrative Reaſon, is not ſo Ordinarily in a <hi>moment.</hi> This Certainty is Ordinarily hatched out of Topicks, and moſt Propoſitions even of Divine Truth uſually at firſt appear to the Soul <hi>probable,</hi> before they appear indubitably certain. The Gray hairs of that other cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty (which is diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Moral Certainty</hi>) rarely grow up in a Night. This being granted, which every one expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienceth. Suppoſe but a <hi>Convocation,</hi> or a <hi>Colledge of Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours,</hi> to determine <hi>de Omnibus agendis,</hi> of all things to be Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly Obſerved, and done. To what purpoſe ſhould any read, or ſtudy any Books for the diſquiſition of Truth, as to any part of a Propoſition; for when he hath done, ſo long as the thing to be done appears to him but <hi>probably</hi> Lawful, or <hi>probably unlawful,</hi> which it muſt do before it appears to him indubitably, and out of all Queſtion the one, or the other, he is according to this
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109403:35"/>Opinion bound in Conſcience (if he be by Superiours Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) to do quite contrary to what he Judgeth Lawful, if he be not indubitably certain it is unlawful. What need he Read and ſtudy the Scriptures, as to Matter of Practice? When he hath found out the moſt he can there, ſome or other will diſpute the Truth of what he thinks he hath found out; and if ſo, it is diſputable; and if it be diſputable, his Notion is not indubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (according to this Novel Doctrine) and he is bound to do what he is bidden. So as his Notion ſhall be cruſh'd in the Egg, and never be ſuffered to hatch into a Demonſtration, or indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table certainty, and all his Reading for the finding out of the truth, ſhall ſerve for nothing but to torture him, with a continual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, and checking of Conſcience, which will never let a Man be quiet whiles he Acteth in Repugnancy to it. Will any ſay yet, he ſhall do well to <hi>Read,</hi> to perſwade himſelf of the Lawfulneſs of what he is Commanded. Suppoſe another Superiour ſhould then come and Command him the quite contrary (as he may doubtleſs.) But it may be ſome will ſay, ſo long as he by Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely perſwades himſelf it is <hi>Lawful;</hi> not neceſſary antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daneouſly to the Superiours Command, he is well enough; he may firſt Obey the one, then the other: But how ſhall a Man be able ſo to govern himſelf, as by Reading to ſecure himſelf that he ſhall not convince himſelf the thing is neceſſary? Thus accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this abſurd poſition, we may part with all the practical part of Scripture, and, as the Popiſh Proſelytes uſe to do, burn our Bibles, onely excepting ſome few Precepts about <hi>Obedience to Superiours,</hi> in that will lye the whole Duty of Man, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe the Scripture ſaith (unleſs in things unlawful, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law and light of Nature) muſt be expounded with a <hi>Salvo. This you muſt not do, except Superiours Command. This you muſt do, unleſs Superiours Command the contrary.</hi> If not all Scripture, we would willingly know where theſe Divines will ſet the Limits? Will they ſay (as indeed they do) <hi>it is onely in things in their own Nature indifferent;</hi> this looks like ſomething, but is indeed nothing: Who ſhall be Judge of thoſe things which are ſo? Shall the Inferiours Conſcience, as to his practice, be Judge? Then the Queſtion is granted on our ſide. Shall the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Judge, for the Inferiours practice? Then the Limitation ſignifieth nothing. How any will get out of this Nooſe, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109403:36"/>Divine; but enough is ſaid in this caſe, we Conclude it An <hi>abſurd, unreaſonable, unſcriptural, Popiſh, Brutiſh Aſſertion, for any to affirm it Lawful, for Chriſtians under any Circumſtances, in Matters of Worſhip eſpecially, to Act contrary to what in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Judgment of his own Conſcience, formed from Arguments which to him appear very probable, he Judgeth to be Lawful from intrinſecal Nature, affections, and adjuncts of the Action</hi> Let us now ſhortly enquire what inconveniencies our Opinion in this caſe is incumbred with, or are charged upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The Grand Objection anſwered. This Principle doth not take away all Power from Magiſtrates, nor at all diſſolve the Bonds of any due Obedience. The Magiſtrates Power opened, granted, limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; he hath no power to Judge as to the Inferiours practice, what is, or is not indifferent. The ſtrange variety of conformable Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in ſtating, and determining the Queſtion. The Reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Neceſſity of Indulgence. Dr. <hi>Aſhton's</hi> late Book ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, his Notion of Perſecution inquired into, the true No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. An Introduction to the next Caſe.</head>
               <p>§. 1. THE Common and Grand, and we think, the onely valuable Objection againſt this Propoſition, is, <hi>That this Principle taketh away all power from Superiours,</hi> and diſſolves all Inferiours Obligations to <hi>Obedience;</hi> and this we hear of often enough, and it were Objection enough if it were but half true. But let us go down into this Field, and ſee whether the Principle be ſo guilty, according to the Cry againſt it. That which they Offer in Juſtification of this, is, <q>
                     <hi>That the World is now grown ſo cunning, that there is hardly any thing which can be Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Superiours, but the Wit of Man will find out ſome proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Arguments to prove that it is unlawful, which if it be once ſo proved, the Inferiour is diſcharged from his Obedience. Again, they ſay, All things are either Neceſſary, Lawful, or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfull. for things Neceſſary, and unlawful, let Superiours Command what they pleaſe, the Inferiours muſt not Omit things neceſſary, nor do
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109403:36"/>things unlawful. If the Superiour holds his Peace, the Inferiour muſt do the former, and forbear the latter; ſo as the Superiour hath onely a proper power as to things indifferent. Take away this, and you leave him nothing.</hi>
                  </q> This is the ſtrength of what we find ſaid here and there in more words.</p>
               <p>§. 2. In Anſwer to both which we ſay, 1. That it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that God hath not ſet up Superiours for Nothings, there is in them a Power, and a great Power to Command, and Obedience to their Commands is a Duty, a great Duty. This is not Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted betwixt us; now to open wherein the Power of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate lyes, we ſay, 1. That the Magiſtrate being <hi>as a God</hi> to us, and God's Vice-gerents, his firſt and great work unqueſtionably lyeth in ſeeing that the Commands of God be fulfilled, both his <hi>Moral Laws,</hi> and his <hi>Poſitive Laws about Divine Worſhip;</hi> and this alone (if his Power were no more) were not onely a Noble Employment, but full, and ſufficient to employ the Head and Hands of any Mortal Man in any large Juriſdiction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas as to the Government of Political Bodies, and Matters meerly Circumſtantial concerning the Worſhip of God, which are yet neceſſary to the upholding of Polities, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice in them; and without which, in Matters of Religion, the Worſhip of God either could not at all be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, or at leaſt, not ſo performed, but that in the Eye of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe and Reaſon it would be Judged by the moſt,. diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and indecently performed. In theſe things Gods Word hath onely generally determined, and the Superiour hath a confeſſed Power in theſe things (which even the higheſt Non-Conformiſts will grant) to make particular Laws in theſe things; and indeed rightly conſidered, theſe are but <hi>Laws</hi> in things <hi>neceſſary,</hi> though not <hi>Originally,</hi> yet upon ſuppoſition of the general Commands of Scripture. 'Tis one thing to Create <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing to Command that things be done in the Church <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently</hi> and <hi>in Order.</hi> The <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of things in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neither muſt nor can ariſe but from <hi>the Law of Nature, the Common ſenſe of Chriſtians, and the particular guiſe and Cuſtom of places.</hi> Now, the Magiſtrate hath an undoubted Power to Command Circumſtantials of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> that is, which are truly ſo, antecedent to his Command. Is this no Power, and proper to him, think we?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:109403:37"/>3. We ſay, that if the Superiour Judgeth a thing thus neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in purſuit of the general Rules of Gods Word, if they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be ſo, the Inferiour is bound in Conſcience, <hi>to do,</hi> or to <hi>omit them.</hi> If the <hi>Superiour onely Judgeth them ſo,</hi> it is his Duty to Command them. If the Inferiour cannot Judge ſo of them, if he Judgeth them in their Circumſtances, but ſuch as he may do, or Omit, he is bound to do them, or omit them (according to the Nature of the Superiours Precept.) But if the Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Judgeth them unlawful for him to do, though this his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be formed but from probable Arguments (that is, ſuch as to him ſo appear) not from indubitably certain Arguments; he cannot <hi>Obey,</hi> but is bound patiently to ſubmit to the penalty im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon him for Diſobedience. So that theſe Objections are perfectly vain, and no incumbrances at all upon our Propoſition.</p>
               <p>§. 3. But we ſay, It is one thing for us to allow a Power in Superiours to determine us, where both we and they agree the thing in its own Nature, and cloathed with ſuch Circumſtances, of a middle and indifferent Nature; And quite another thing for us, (and that as to the things of God too) and ſuch things, where for doing, or not doing, the danger of ſin and Eternal Damnation lyeth, to make him <hi>Our Judge</hi> what is, and what is not <hi>Indifferent.</hi> It is impoſſible any intelligent Soul ſhould allow the latter to his Superiour without alſo making him <hi>a Judge both of Good and Evil.</hi> For <hi>Indifferency</hi> being a middle betwixt thoſe two <hi>extremes,</hi> there's no poſſibility of his being a Judge of it without alſo determining concerning the extremes. And if we could allow this, we ſhould as to private Chriſtians uſe ſee little need of the Scriptures, for the Superiour muſt Interpret them too, or all will come to nothing.</p>
               <p>§. 4. Nay, we further ſay, that there may be ſome ſtreſſes of Providence, as to which the being of Polities, and the Preſervation of Juſtice lyes at ſtake, where ſome things may be Lawful which in Ordinary Caſes God will not allow. <hi>You know</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>what</hi> David <hi>did when he was an hungry, how he did eat the Shew-bread, which was not Lawful for any</hi> (in Ordinary Caſes) <hi>to eat, but for the Prieſts onely.</hi> It was a Caſe of real Neceſſity to ſave his Life: It would have been a ſin, both in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> upon a lighter pretence to have done it, and for the Prieſt to have ſuffered it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:109403:37"/>§. 5. We have been the more willing to ſearch this buſineſs to the bottom, becauſe of that andacious Liberty, which ſome have taken, either openly to aſſert, or cunningly to inſinuate the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; a thing (undoubtedly) of as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l a tendency as can well be imagined, leading directly to <hi>a Blind Obedience,</hi> one of the Capital Errors of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and poſſibly a more ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, and brutiſh Errour, than any other which they have, as deveſting Man of his Humane Nature, and that which is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of moſt other of their abominable Doctrines, any abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as Naturally following that firſt, as the Thread follows the Needle: If it can be ſuppoſed, that there may be a Superiour abſurd in his <hi>Sentiments</hi> or <hi>Practice;</hi> which that it may be, we need no other Evidence than what the Infallible Choyce it ſelf hath given the wiſer part of the World often enough Evidence of.</p>
               <p>§. 6. We have been amazed to Obſerve how tenderly Modern Writers have touched this Queſtion. Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> indeed, as we have before ſaid, is peremptory enough againſt us, to that degree as we find none of his Poſterity in that thing approving his ſaying. The Author of the <hi>Pulpit Conceptions, Popular decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> fairly skips it over, telling us what ſhould be done by us, if we ſcruple our Obedience; but not a word what we ſhould do, if we from probable Arguments judge the thing unlawful. <hi>Freeman</hi> (as we ſhewed before) is peremptory enough beyond all <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Religion.</hi> But another, writing a Book profeſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about <hi>Tenderneſs of Conſcience,</hi> when he comes to Anſwer the Caſe of Doubting, ſpeaks almoſt to every thing elſe, but (prudently) leaves out this Caſe. Others tell us, that if the thing Commanded be <hi>apparently, demonſtratively, indiſputably evil,</hi> if it tends to <hi>debauch us</hi> in <hi>our Sentiments concerning the God-head,</hi> &amp;c. we muſt not Obey; but if otherwiſe, either they ſay nothing, or elſe tell us we ought to Obey. The Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fulwood,</hi> are the onely two Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Divines that we have met with, daring to ſtate the Caſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, and ſpeaking to it in the Dialect of Proteſtants. But others, in their Writings, either ſhew little of <hi>Divines,</hi> ſtating the Caſe falſly, and not ſpeaking <hi>ad idem.</hi> Or little of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> ſaying that which no Proteſtant Divines ever durſt ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them.</p>
               <p>§. 6. And from hence to every conſiderate Reader, will be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109403:38"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:109403:38"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:109403:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:109403:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:109403:40"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:109403:40"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:109403:41"/>inevitably concluded the <hi>Reaſonableneſs,</hi> if not the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of an <hi>Indulgence</hi> from all Superiours, who will think themſelves under any Obligation to the <hi>Royal Law of Love.</hi> For as that Law will Oblige them <hi>not to ſuffer ſin in their Inferiours,</hi> Lev. 19.17. So. it will alſo Oblige them not to lay <hi>a ſtumbling block before them that are weak,</hi> by which they both <hi>ſin againſt Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.9, 10, 11, 12, 13. and do not walk <hi>Charitably,</hi> Rom. 14.15. Nor yet <hi>to make them to ſuffer,</hi> becauſe <hi>they dare not ſin:</hi> For to Act againſt their Conſcience (though but Opining) is ſin. For all this Suffering muſt unqueſtionably be <hi>a Suffering for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſake,</hi> for to depart from Iniquity is unqueſtionably a piece of Righteouſneſs. Hence though the Superiour upon the firſt Account be bound to Oblige his Inferiours by his Civil San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to do all that which the Law of God hath made <hi>neceſſary</hi> for them to do, and to forbear what the ſame Law hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, otherwiſe <hi>he ſhould ſuffer ſin upon them:</hi> Yet if he thinks fit to Command other things in Religion, which (poſſibly) him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſome of his Inferiours Judge <hi>not ſinful,</hi> and tendent to ſome State or <hi>Decency,</hi> but the want of them makes not the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite <hi>indecent</hi> or <hi>diſorderly,</hi> according to any Light or Law of Nature, or the general guiſe and Cuſtom of the place; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other his Inferiours Judge ſo far from tendency to <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> that they from Arguments, which to them appear ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry probable, judge them <hi>ſinful</hi> and <hi>unlawful,</hi> and ſo capable of no ſuch Notion, how he can poſſibly exact an Obedience to any ſuch Commands, without</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Either putting his Inferiours upon ſin, and continual diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of their Conſciences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Or making them Sufferers, becauſe they dare not ſin againſt God;</hi> which is (as we ſaid before) <hi>a ſpecies</hi> (at leaſt) <hi>of Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for Righteouſneſs-ſake.</hi> We muſt confeſs our ſelves (which poſſibly is our weakneſs) not Divines ſufficient to underſtand, and ſhould thank any one that could inform us. Now, betwixt theſe there lyeth no <hi>Medium,</hi> but a <hi>Gracious Indulgence,</hi> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Remedy, which His Moſt <hi>Excellent Majeſty</hi> hath ſuited to this fore Evil.</p>
               <p>§. 7. And here we would have finiſhed our Diſcourſe, but for a late Book, called, <hi>The Caſes of Scandal and Perſecution,</hi> which yet hath no ſuch depths in it, as to ask us long time to ſound.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:109403:41"/>The Author ſpends one part of his Book, in perſwading us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what we know none ever doubted, <hi>viz. That in Caſe the thing Commanded us be by us Judged Lawful</hi> (for that he beggs all along) <hi>we ought not to forbear doing it, becauſe ſome of our Brethren would be grieved and teachy at it, provided our doing of it laid no ſtumbling-block before them,</hi> to <hi>give them Occaſion to ſin againſt God.</hi> We would fain know what Non-Conformiſt ever ſaid the contrary. Thus Men Exerciſe themſelves in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates with fancied Enemies, for really the Doctor hath none in this Caſe that ever we heard of. The Second Part of his Book comes nearer what we laſt ſaid, and notwithſtanding all he ſaith, we do think, That it is at leaſt a <hi>Mute Caſe</hi> (as they ſay in Law) <hi>Whether the forcing any to Suffer, becauſe he cannot, or dare not Act contrary to the Opinion of his Conſcience, guided by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which to him appear probable, be not Perſecuting.</hi> To paſs by his other impertinencies, allowing him to uſe a very true Method to try the iſſue, in fixing the Notion of Perſecution, we there joyn Iſſue with him.</p>
               <p>§. 8. In his 44 p. he tells us, <hi>Perſecution is an Inflicting of outward temporal Evils for the Exerciſe of true Religion.</hi> The <hi>Genus</hi> we agree, and think he might have ſhortned the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by leaving out <hi>Outward</hi> and <hi>Temporal,</hi> becauſe no Man can Inflict any other Evils upon his Brother. The difference he makes to lye in thoſe words [For the Exerciſe of the True Religion.] But why might not our Saviours terms have been taken, <hi>for Righteouſneſs ſake?</hi> Yet if <hi>Religion</hi> be taken in the larger Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, for doing <hi>any part of our Duty,</hi> in which we bounden to towards God, we cannot fault the Deſcription; but this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription makes but the <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition. The <hi>Minor</hi> muſt be this, <hi>[But the Outward Temporal Evils.] Impriſonments, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation of Eccleſiaſtical preferments, pecuniary mulcts, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings, Revilings, Reproachful ſpeeches.] Inflicted upon Non-Conformiſts are not inflicted upon them, for doing any part, of that Duty, wherein they are bounden to God.</hi> There are very many Non-Conformiſts will put the <hi>Doctor</hi> to prove this, and tell him, It is a <hi>piece of Righteouſneſs, a part of true Religion, and every Mans bounden Duty toward God, not to Act contrary to what his Conſcience, Gods Vice-gerent, in him, tells him, and that upon Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments which appear very probable to him, is Lawful.</hi> And in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109403:42"/>Matters of Gods Worſhip alſo to do According to what his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tells him is the Will of God he ſhould do. And we take Notice too of an Excellent paſſage in the Doctors Book, p. 45. <hi>l. ult &amp; penult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>That God hath as much Right to appoint the way of his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as to be Worſhipped.</hi>
                  </q> A paſſage we are ſo much in Love with, that it is one of our greateſt Topicks to prove many things Commanded us <hi>probably unlawful.</hi> Prayer is Worſhip: <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Forms,</hi> or by words formed firſt in our own Hearts, is a <hi>way of Worſhip.</hi> Now, ſay we, God hath as much <hi>right</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe <hi>the way</hi> as <hi>the Worſhip,</hi> and hath done it. <hi>As every Man hath received the gift,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ſo let him Miniſter,</hi> 1. Pet. 4.10. Praying and Preaching <hi>are Worſhip.</hi> The doing theſe Acts in a peculiar Habit appropriated to theſe Actions, <hi>is a way of Worſhip; And God</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Doctor</hi>) <hi>hath as much right to appoint the way of his Worſhip, as the Worſhip.</hi> The like might be ſaid of the other Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>§. 9. But ſuppoſe we allow the Doctors Deſcription of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection.</hi> The next Queſtion is, how we ſhall know what is <hi>True Religion:</hi> Who ſhall be the Judge? Shall the Scriptures ? But who ſhall Interpret the Scriptures as to a Chriſtians private Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice? Shall the Superiours? Then certainly there was never any <hi>Perſecution</hi> in the World: For it were very uncharitable to preſume, that any Superiour ſhould puniſh another for the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of what himſelf owned to be the true Religion. We have more Charity for <hi>Bonner</hi> himſelf. Shall the Inferiour be Judge what is true <hi>Religion?</hi> Then I fear the Doctor will be caſt; many of them will ſay, they are <hi>miſchievouſly, and violently Proſecuted, Impriſoned, Puniſhed, Reviled,</hi> for what they Judge <hi>the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the True Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 10. The upſhot of this Diſcourſe is, that who they be, who are truly guilty of <hi>Perſecuting,</hi> will not be determined till the Day of Judgment, when God ſhall determine, which was the <hi>True Religion;</hi> and whether Men truly ran thoſe hazards, becauſe they were afraid of ſinning againſt God. In the mean time, as to us, he is <hi>Perſecuted,</hi> who can truly ſay, <hi>That he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers for doing any thing, which he thinks he ſhould ſin againſt God if he did not do; and for forbearing any thing, which he truly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s he ſhould ſin againſt God if he ſhould do.</hi> And we believe,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109403:42"/>that thoſe who thus Suffer, though another day they ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged by God to have been in a miſtake, and ſo not Perſecuted, yet as to what they have done, will be Judged guilty of no more than an Humane Infirmity.</p>
               <p>§.11. We have ſo much Charity, as to believe, that that <hi>Popiſh Prieſt</hi> who ſuffers according to the Law, for <hi>Seducing:</hi> If he can truly ſay, that he did believe, Gods Word Obliged him to do what he did, may properly enough ſay he is <hi>Perſecuted;</hi> but we alſo believe, that God will not Judge ſo another day, and that the Magiſtrate doth but his Duty; becauſe by Gods Law none ought to be endured that entice others to <hi>Idolatry.</hi> But whoſo makes another to Suffer becauſe he durſt not ſin againſt God, Acting contrary to what his Conſcience judgeth unlawful from probable Arguments, we believe far leſs excuſable, becauſe there's no neceſſity upon him to lay any ſuch Commands, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them by any ſuch penalties. But there does lye a neceſſity of ſuffering in this Caſe upon the Inferiour to avoid ſinning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Conſcience: whether his Conſcience be in the right or in the wrong, will be determined another day. In the mean time he ſhould ſin, if he ſhould not hearken to it; to avoid which, he ſuffers, which is ſo far as he can poſſibly Judge to ſuffer <hi>for Righteouſneſs ſake.</hi> After the ſaying of which we think little more need be ſaid to the Doctor's Book.</p>
               <p>§. 12. To Conclude our Diſcourſe upon this Queſtion, we have obſerved in all thoſe almoſt who have wrote for Conformity, great inſiſting upon the Authority of former, and preſent Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and the Teſtimonies of many Divines, dead, or alive; ſome of which they tell us were <hi>Old Non-Conformiſts.</hi> And this hath been the general Method of all late Writers almoſt, to paſs over all our, and our Fore-Fathers Arguments, and in Order to make us as odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the World, as they would have us; to repreſent us as ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and differing from the Church in all Ages, yea, from our ſelves, and our Fore-Fathers, &amp;c. To what better purpoſe than this, theſe in artificial Arguments are uſed we cannot tell, unleſs thoſe that bring them have a little tincture of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Doctrine we before ſhewed at large;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That extrinſick Arguments may make an Action appear probably Lawful; though at the ſame time from intrinſick Arguments, we Judge it probably unlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:109403:43"/>A Pill ſo nauſeous, ſo brutiſh, as it is impoſſible we ſhould ſwallow it, till we have vomited up our rational Souls. And 'tis the more odious to us becauſe it is of ſuch affinity to the deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Blind Obedience</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But to defeat theſe men of any hopes of prevailing by ſuch <hi>Mediums,</hi> we will ſhortly enquire into another Queſtion, though not the ſame, yet of great. <hi>Cognation</hi> with this which we have now ſo largely diſcuſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI. Second Queſt.</hi> Whether it be Naturally poſſible for any Perſon in a Practical Propoſition to judge that part probably Lawful from extrinſick. Arguments; the contrary to which he at the ſame time Judgeth probably unlawful from intrinſick Arguments. <hi>The Queſtion opened. The Opinions of</hi> Vaſquez, Sanchez. The Negative part of the Queſtion maintained, becauſe this is contrary to the Principles of a Rational Soul. The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>§. 1. WE have had Occaſions once and again to hint the known diſtinction between <hi>Speculative and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Propoſitions:</hi> Divines call thoſe Propoſitions Speculative, whoſe uſe and advantage is onely terminated in Speculation and Knowledge, and from whence nothing in Practice is Directed. They call thoſe <hi>Practical,</hi> whoſe end is the guidance and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Practice. But Speculative Propoſitions muſt be again diſtinguiſhed into ſuch. 1. <hi>From which no Obligation ariſeth to the Exerciſe of any rational Act of ours:</hi> Such as theſe. <hi>That there was ſuch a City as Troy,</hi> ſuch a King of <hi>France,</hi> as <hi>Pipin,</hi> &amp;c. with a thouſand ſuch like. 2. Such, the Truth of which infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the performance of ſome Rational Action of ours, and ſuch as is our Duty towards God, as theſe. <hi>That the Scriptures are the Word of God .That Chriſt is the Eternally exiſtent Son of God.</hi> But our Queſtion relates to none of theſe, but to ſuch Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions onely where the Queſtion is, <hi>Whether it be Lawful for me to do this or that, or no:</hi> This is that we mean by <hi>a Practical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 2. In our Diſcourſe upon the former Queſtion we have alſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:109403:43"/>often hinted, what we mean by <hi>Extrinſecal,</hi> and <hi>Intrinſcal,</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. The ſingular Judgment of every intelligent Perſon's Conſcience is formed from ſome Arguments, drawn either from Principles of Reaſon, or Propoſitions of Scripture. Theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments are either from plain <hi>letter of Scripture,</hi> or <hi>Principles of Reaſon</hi> accounted Infallible, which fix the Conſcience. Or elſe they are drawn from <hi>Logical Topicks,</hi> and called <hi>Dialectick Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments,</hi> or <hi>Probable:</hi> For <hi>Optimus Philoſophus nondum naſcitur.</hi> We ſay, Theſe probable Arguments are again either <hi>Intrinſecal,</hi> called <hi>Artificial Arguments</hi> by the Logicians, fetched from the Cauſes, Effects, Conſequents, Adjuncts, or other Affections of the Subject or predicate in the Queſtion. 2. Such as are meerly <hi>Extrinſick.</hi> Logicians call them <hi>In-artificial,</hi> becauſe every Dunce may bring them, they have no Art at all in them. Divines call them <hi>Extrinſecal,</hi> becauſe they are Forreign to the in ward parts of the Queſtion, and the Soul that brings them. Theſe are ſuch as are fetched from <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony of others; Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Fathers, School-men, former,</hi> or <hi>Modern Divines,</hi> &amp;c. Now, it is demonſtratively Truth, That it is poſſible, that a ſoul ſhould have a great many Arguments appearing to it very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſuch as it cannot Anſwer, and ſcarcely believes that any other can, to prove a thing unlawful; and at the ſame time meet with many Teſtimonies and ſayings of <hi>Fathers, Councils, School-men, Caſuiſts, Ancienter,</hi> or <hi>more Modern Divines,</hi> ſpeaking the thing Lawful. It is the Caſe of the <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> this day. Though they meet not with any <hi>Fathers, Councils,</hi> &amp;c. who judge the things Lawful, which they do judge unlawful; yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preſent Divines they do meet with, yet they cannot but from Intrinſick, Dialectick Arguments think the things utterly unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p>§. 3. Now, the Queſtion is, in this Caſe, what they ſhall do ? They do not deny but it is their Duty, upon the Teſtimonies of <hi>Superiours,</hi> and their Commands; or hearing the Judgment of ſo many Learned Men of another Mind, to examine again their own Arguments, and to try them to the utmoſt: But ſuppoſing at laſt (which is the Caſe) the things yet ſeem to them from very probable Arguments <hi>unlawful,</hi> what ſhall they do? <hi>They may</hi> (ſay the <hi>Jeſuites</hi>) do <hi>ſuch things, or not do them;</hi> For this is the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites help</hi> againſt the abominable abſurdity of Acting contrary to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:109403:44"/>an <hi>Opining Conſcience.</hi> They ſay, <hi>While it it but an Opinion, a Man may Opine both contradictory parts of the ſame Queſtion;</hi> the one upon <hi>Intrinſick,</hi> the other upon <hi>Extrinſick</hi> Arguments; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (as we ſhewed before) <hi>the Opinion which is formed upon Artificial, proper, intrinſick Arguments muſt needs be more probable;</hi> Yet they ſay, a man is not tyed up to <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>minus</hi> in the Caſe. <hi>It is ground enough</hi> (ſay they) <hi>for any man to act Conſcientiouſly, if the thing appear any way probable, he is not bound to act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which he judgeth more probable.</hi> So that, ſay they, if a thing appear <hi>probably Lawful,</hi> by <hi>Extrinſick Arguments the Opinion of ſome Doctors,</hi> &amp;c. we may do it, though at the ſame time we judge it never ſo unlawful from <hi>Intrinſick, Artificial</hi> Arguments, fetched from all the Topicks in Logick, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſubject, and Praedictate of the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>§. 9. The Caſe is ſo weighty, and this Opinion ſo unmanly, and Brutiſh, that it is reaſonable we ſhould bring forth one or two, who ſhall vouch for themſelves and their Brethren, that this is what they ſay and hold. Let <hi>Vaſquez</hi> (a Man of no ſmall repute amongſt them) ſpeak firſt, out of his Diſput. in 12 <hi>ae. diſput.</hi> 62. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.<hi>n.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Tertio Obſervandum eſt, eum qui habet aſſenſum unius partis propoſitionis, per propria &amp; intrinſeca principia etiamſi aſſenſus ille tantum ſit probabilis, non poſſe habere aſſenſum alterius pactis per intrinſeca, &amp; propria principia: bene tamen poſſe per externa principia exiſtimari oppoſitam partem eſſe probabilem. v. plura</hi> ibid. &amp; <hi>cap.</hi> 40. n. 15.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sanchez</hi> ſings the ſame Song, <hi>Op. Moral. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>n.</hi> 12. <q>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum fundamentum eſt ut duas Opiniones ediametro ſibi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicentes idem intellectus judicet probabiles, aut aequè, aut alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram probabiliorem;</hi>
                  </q> he ſhews this is according to the Opinion of <hi>Azorius</hi> and <hi>Vaſquez</hi> (before quoted.) And then goeth on, telling us, that he ſeeth no Reaſon, but the ſame Underſtanding may judge the contradictory parts of the ſame Propoſition both probably true, or falſe; lawful, or unlawful; and that Experience proves it. But this is ſurely a Note above <hi>Ela,</hi> and a Riddle in Philoſophy. The <hi>Jeſuites</hi> being pinched with that obvious Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>That then the ſame Soul, and at the ſame time, and the ſame thing may aſſent to contradictions;</hi> and blow hot and cold, bleſs and curſe, with the ſame breath: They think to avoid it by
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109403:44"/>telling us, that the Underſtanding affirmeth neither part, we won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how it ſhould <hi>Opine</hi> then?</p>
               <p>§. 10. This is a great point in <hi>Popery</hi> (<hi>Jeſuitiſme</hi> eſpecially) and of no ſmall gain to them, for by this mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they can reſolve Caſes as they liſt, abſolve Mens Conſciences as they pleaſe, and Interpret the Law of God into a very pleaſing conſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tency with the Luſts, and Paſſions of all Men: If it were admitted for true, it would open a wide door for Men to do what they liſted, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any check or controul of Conſcience. There being but few things in practice, which one Doctor or other, under one Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or other, hath not judged Lawful. <hi>There are few actions but are diſputable,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Freeman,</hi> in his <hi>Reaſonableneſs of Divine Service,</hi> p. 33. And if one or more Doctors affirm it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful (ſay the Popiſh Caſuiſts) the private Chriſtian may aſſent to it as <hi>probably Lawful,</hi> though at the ſame time, from <hi>Artificial</hi> Intrinſick Arguments, formed in his own Breaſt, he judgeth it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably unlawful. And we wiſh, ſome profeſſing themſelves <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divines,</hi> did not cant after this Tune (though it may be they will not as the Papiſts) reſt it upon the Opinion of <hi>one Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> but many Learned Men; if they did not a little linger after this, we cannot tell what means their conſtant choaking of us, with the <hi>bare Opinions</hi> of others contrary to ours, in which ſurely we are no further concerned, than as quickned by them to re-examine our own Intrinſecal Arguments more ſtrictly.</p>
               <p>§. 11. We muſt declare our ſelves in the Negative of this Queſtion, and do affirm, <q>
                     <hi>That it is Naturally impoſſible for a Rational Soul, in a practical propoſition, to Judge that part from Extrinſecal in-artificial Arguments Probably Lawful, which, at the ſame time, from Intrinſecal artificial Arguments, formed in its own Breaſt, it judgeth Probably <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful;</hi> and in this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we are confirmed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 12. Becauſe <hi>it is contrary to the innate Principles of a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Soul.</hi> 1. We ſuppoſe every one will without difficulty grant it a Principle of a Reaſonble Soul, <hi>To Conclude nothing but from Rational Foundations: Reaſon is a Power within us, Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Concluſions from Principles.</hi> It acknowledged <hi>there is a God,</hi> and that <hi>he hath revealed his will</hi> in thoſe Books which we call <hi>The Holy Scriptures,</hi> and muſt acknowledge it the moſt reaſonable thing imaginable, that he ſhould be acknowledged <hi>true in his word.</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:109403:45"/>Hence it concludes many Propoſitions of Faith, upon the bare Authority of God revealing them, and exerciſeth it ſelf no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than <hi>to compare Spiritual things with Spiritual.</hi> But having not that Evidence for other things, it maketh uſe of <hi>inbred Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and from thoſe Principles raiſeth Concluſions. Now, let us conſider from what Principle it is poſſible; that <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch a Concluſion as this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That is probably Lawful for me to do, which ſuch or ſuch Divines (be they more or fewer, more or leſs Learned) think is Lawful; or which Superiours require (under that Notion) notwithſtanding any Artificial, Intrinſick Arguments which make my own Conſcience Judge it very probably unlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It muſt be this: <hi>Thoſe Doctors,</hi> or <hi>thoſe Superiours, know bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than I.</hi> Doth Reaſon in a man allow any ſuch concluſion? <hi>Modeſty</hi> indeed upon ſuch an Account, may make a reaſonable Soul Jealous, and Suſpitious, and to iſſue out <hi>a Writ</hi> for a better enquiry upon its Arguments, but it is impoſſible that it ſhould reſt in ſuch a Concluſion to guide its Practice, where the hazard of the Eternal Felicity of a Soul is concerned. Reaſon ſpeaketh in the Language of <hi>Job</hi> to his Friends, <hi>Job</hi> 12.3. <hi>I have <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as well as you;</hi> and be it what it will, <hi>gradually</hi> compared with all the Doctors reaſon, it is <hi>the Candle of the Lord ſet up in my Soul, according to the Light of which I muſt walk.</hi> Or in the words of <hi>Elihu,</hi> Job 32.8. <hi>There is a Spirit in Man, and the Inſpiration of the Almighty gives him <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding:</hi> Reaſon ſaith, <hi>Bring forth your ſtrong arguments, and I will anſwer them;</hi> or <hi>hear mine, and do you anſwer me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 13. Beſides, Reaſon ſaith, If this were belonging to all <hi>Doctors,</hi> or all Superiours, that <hi>Wiſdom</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith) <hi>muſt dye with them,</hi> how is it they are not agreed amongſt themſelves? Such, and ſuch are on my ſide; if it doth not agree to all Superiours, and all <hi>Doctors,</hi> how ſhall I be aſſured, that it more agrees to thoſe on the adverſe ſide, than to thoſe on my fide; to Dr. <hi>Vaſquez</hi> more than to <hi>Pope Adrian?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. 14 Further, (ſaith Reaſon) do not know and ſee, that there are many <hi>Doctores,</hi> who are not <hi>Docti,</hi> and that many Learned men in all Ages have been in Factions? doth not Dr. <hi>Vaſquez</hi> himſelf tell me, in 12. <hi>diſp.</hi> 62. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>That he cannot deny but a whole rout of Doctors may embrace an Opinion without any Reaſon, againſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:109403:45"/>whom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>another Doctor of great Authority may bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Schools, an Opinion maturely deliberated? Vaſquez</hi> need not be Credited, if we did not upon Experience find daily, that not one of many Doctors examines things, but follows ſome Leader, as diligently as Sheep do one another over an Hedge; that many either underſtand not the true Queſtion, about which they will be Writing in this Age, or of choice miſtake it, &amp; write far more paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion than Divinity, or Reaſon, which made <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> &amp; ſome others of his Brethren deliver their Opinion, <hi>That a Learned Man may act according to his own Opinion, though contrary to the Opinions of other Doctors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§.15. Reaſon tells a Man, that Reaſon is not entailed to the Relation of a <hi>Superiour,</hi> or the <hi>Degree of a Doctor. Animae rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onales ſunt aequales in perfectione Subſtantiali,</hi> and Superiority or Doctorſhip make no difference. Experience teacheth us, that improvement by Study, makes not a difference, as to the Exerciſe of Reaſon, between all Superiours and Inferiours; nor between all thoſe who are <hi>Doctors</hi> and no <hi>Doctors.</hi> It remaineth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the particular Reaſon of every Soul muſt ſtand up in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of it ſelf, eſpecially in matters of Practice, as to which Eternal Salvation or Damnation are concerned; ſo as it is not Naturally poſſible, that a Reaſonable Soul ſhould from Forreign Authority conclude a thing <hi>probably Lawful,</hi> which from its own Rational concluſions it judgeth <hi>probably <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 16, But further yet, certainly it is repugnant to the connate Principles of Reaſonable Souls, <hi>to aſſert contraries, both at the ſame time to be true,</hi> becauſe it is of the Nature of contraries to deſtroy one another. Now, the Underſtanding which ſhall thus aſſert, muſt at the ſame time ſpeak theſe two things, which are manifeſt contradictions: <hi>This is Lawful. This is not Lawful.</hi> I think and Judge it <hi>Lawful,</hi> becauſe <hi>A, B, C, D,</hi> &amp;c. ſay ſo. I think it <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> becauſe my own Reaſon, <hi>comparing things Spiritual with Spiritual, or concluding from confeſſed Principles, tells me it is ſo.</hi> Muſt not this be a very odd Soul, that can Diſcourſe after this rate? <hi>Vaſquez</hi> was aware of this, and thought to avoid it, by denying theſe two Propoſitions to be <hi>Contradictory, viz.</hi> 1. <hi>This is probably Lawful.</hi> 2. <hi>This is probably unlawful.</hi> But he deludeth, and his fallacy lyes in the word <hi>probably,</hi> which in the Queſtion ſignifieth not the <hi>Affection of the propoſition,</hi> but the <hi>Nature of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109403:46"/>the Arguments, or Complexion of the Conſcience.</hi> The Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (let the Jeſuite ſay what he will) muſt ſay, <hi>This is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> and <hi>This is unlawful,</hi> of the ſame thing, and at the ſame time' and theſe are perfect contradictions. The Notion of <hi>Probable</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth to the Underſtanding, not to the <hi>Nature of the Opinion,</hi> and muſt in the Queſtion be Interpreted by <hi>Opinor,</hi> or <hi>Credo,</hi> or ſome ſuch like word; not by <hi>probari poteſt</hi> (which is the Jeſuites cheat) that is, <hi>ſomething may be ſaid, in Argument to prove this thing Lawful,</hi> and <hi>ſomething may alſo be ſaid to prove it unlawful.</hi> Theſe two Propoſitions are not indeed Contradictions; but to ſay, <hi>I think this Lawful,</hi> and at the ſame time to ſay, <hi>I alſo think this is unlawful,</hi> Can be no Language of any Mans Soul, till the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines</hi> have got it, and put out its Eyes, on purpoſe to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſport with it.</p>
               <p>§. 11. Finally, <hi>Is it not the Principle of a Reaſonable Soul, to embrace that which it Judgeth Beſt, either upon the Account of Truth or Righteouſneſs?</hi> Now, where both parts of a Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion appear but <hi>probable. i. e.</hi> Such as ſomething in Argument may be ſaid for either; but one (in appearance to the particular Soul) far more probable, both as to <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> than the other. Is it not contrary to its principles to own and embrace that which it Judgeth leſs true in it ſelf, and conſequently, leſs Righteous to be done? even the Popiſh <hi>School-men</hi> and <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> will confeſs our own Opinion to be more probable, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they moſt abſurdly ſay, That a man is not bound to follow that which probably is more True and Righteous, (ſo great a Power hath Corrupt Intereſt) we conclude therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>That it being Naturally impoſſible for a Reaſonable Soul to act Reaſonably contrary to Naturally Rational Principles, it is alſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally impoſſible for it to Judge at the ſame time, the ſame thing,</hi> probably Lawful, <hi>from in-artificial and Extrinſick Arguments, which it Judgeth</hi> probably, <hi>and more probably unlawful from Artificial intrinſick Arguments.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 12. By this time, we hope we have gained one Poſt (and that not inconſiderable) which we doubt not to make good againſt all the Attaques of Popiſh, or Proteſtant Divines, but ſuch as are onely made from-their <hi>Bitter words,</hi> which wound onely (by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coiling) the malitious hearts of thoſe that caſt them: We have ſhewen that there is (as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith) <hi>a Spirit in every Man, and the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:109403:46"/>Almighty hath given to every one,</hi> a peculiar practick <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> which mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to him be Gods Interpreter, and <hi>the proximate Rule and Guide of all his Actions;</hi> which particular Conſcience acknowledgeth God onely as <hi>its immediate Superiour,</hi> and where the Eternal welfare of the ſoul is concerned in the Action, can neither bow down to the <hi>New Erected Idol</hi> of the <hi>Publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and much leſs, to the private <hi>Conſciences</hi> and <hi>Judgments</hi> of any, to do things which they Judge Lawful, meerly becauſe They ſay they are Lawful, and ſo <hi>will</hi> the Practice of them as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe their Superiours, or ſuch <hi>Doctors</hi> ſay ſo; when as it judgeth the thing wicked and unlawful, from Arguments, which though it cannot call Demonſtrative, and indubitable, yet it ſelf cannot Anſwer, nor ſee Anſwered by any other, ſo as it can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce in the Anſwer as ſufficient, and therefore ſeem to it very probably concluding the thing <hi>unlawful.</hi> We have (as we hope) alſo gained this. <hi>That it is Naturally impoſſible for a reaſonable Soul, at the ſame time, to Judge the ſame thing Lawful, from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>artificial extrinſick Arguments; which from intrinſick Arguments formed within it ſelf, or accepted by it, though formed by others, it Judgeth probably unlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 13. It is therefore the buſineſs of thoſe who think themſelves conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rned to make all the World in Practice uniform, even to a Letter and a Syllable, and a rite, and poſture, not to tell them, <hi>that in caſe the thing</hi> be <hi>diſputable,</hi> or <hi>doubtful,</hi> or not <hi>apparently and demonſtratively evil,</hi> it is their Duty, if <hi>Commanded,</hi> to do it. For this we have ſhewed to be the very <hi>Foundation of Popery,</hi> and a perfect <hi>Innovation</hi> in <hi>Proteſtant Doctrine,</hi> and can be no other than a <hi>Blind Obedience.</hi> But (as we ſaid before) they will be concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to call to <hi>Diſſenters</hi> for <hi>their Arguments,</hi> upon the probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of which to them, the things required ſeem to them <hi>unlawful;</hi> and (if they can) to deſtroy that appearance which they have of probability, which done, they will attain their end, and not before.</p>
               <p>§. 14. The things are many which are required of us, in Order to our having a ſtation in the publick Miniſtry of <hi>England,</hi> ſome of which are queſtioned by ſome, others of them by others; in ſhort, from them theſe Queſtions ariſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Whether the Non-Conformiſts have not probable Arguments to induce their Conſciences to judge it unlawful to perform their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Office in publick Prayer, by the preſcribed forms of other Men.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:109403:47"/>2. <hi>Whether they have not probable Arguments to judge it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to Miniſter before the Lord in a Surplis, or any Habit peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appropriated to the Worſhip of God, to ſign with the ſign of the croſs in Baptiſm, and to Kneel in the Act of Receiving the Lords Supper.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Whether thoſe of them who have been ſolemnly ſet apart to the Miniſtry by Faſting and Prayer, and laying on of hands of a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, can without ſin, ſubmit to a re-ordination by Biſhops, and there be not, at leaſt, very probable Arguments to the contrary.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Whether they have not probable Arguments to induce them to judge it unlawful for them to ſubſcribe, That the Oath, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> The Solemn League and Covenant, <hi>obligeth neither them nor any others, and that it is in it ſelf an unlawful Oath.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Whether they have not probable Arguments to induce them to judge it unlawful for them to declare and ſubſcribe, That they do aſſent and conſent to all and every thing,</hi> or to the uſe <hi>of all and every thing contained in the Common-Prayer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Whether they have not probable Arguments to induce them to judge it unlawful for them to ſubſcribe the Second and Third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle in the</hi> 36 <hi>Canon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>Whether they have not probable Arguments to induce them to judge it unlawful to take the Oath, Ordinarily called, the Oath of Canonical Obedience.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Thoſe who know any thing of the State of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical affairs in England</hi> this day, know, that thoſe who will conform, muſt do all theſe things; and the Non-Conformiſts are ſo far from judging all theſe things Lawful, that they think they have very probable Arguments, why (many of them at leaſt) cannot judge any one of them Lawful; and while they ſo judge, <hi>act they cannot</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Opinion of their own Conſciences, as we have before proved.</p>
               <p>§. 15. Neither do they deſire to talk of Arguments onely in Juſtification of their own <hi>Sullenneſs,</hi> or <hi>Peeviſhneſs,</hi> as they are maliciouſly repreſented by ſome Modern Doctors (far better at Reviling than Diſputing.) Their Arguments, in the firſt Caſe, are many of them in Print, as in Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi>'s <hi>Diſcourſe againſt Set-forms</hi> (many years ſince Printed, but that we know of, never Anſwered) as alſo in Mr. <hi>Calderwood</hi>'s <hi>Altare Damaſ.</hi> never Anſwered neither, and in divers other Books. In the Second Caſe, their Arguments never yet Anſwered, are to be found, In
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:109403:47"/>Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi>'s <hi>Diſcourſes about things Indifferent,</hi> and about
<hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</hi> In Dr. <hi>Ames his</hi> Iriſh <hi>Suit againſt the Ceremonies.</hi> In Mr. <hi>Calderwood</hi>'s <hi>Altare Damaſceum.</hi> In Mr. <hi>Gilleſpie</hi>'s. Diſp. againſt the <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh</hi> Ceremonies. Upon the 3d. Caſe, divers of their Arguments are in <hi>R.A. his Letter to a Friend,</hi> Printed 1661. And <hi>The Serious Review of Presbyters Ordination by Biſhops,</hi> Printed about the ſame time; and in all the other Caſes, Our Brethren know, that Arguments are in Print to prove them <hi>unlawful,</hi> which never yet received any Anſwer. Beſides, as there is a variety of <hi>Mediums,</hi> ſo the ſame ſute not every Fancy, nor are all produced, and the work of them who ſhould undertake to ſhew the Arguments of all not <hi>probable,</hi> would be almoſt infinite.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. What ſhall be done in this Caſe by thoſe Superiours who will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve themſelves, as well as their Inferiours, obliged, recording to the Apoſtles Precept, <hi>To Walk Charitably,</hi> not laying <hi>a ſtumbling-block, before others,</hi> nor doing, as much as in them lyeth, to deſtroy poor Souls, for whom Chriſt dyed. We ſay, what can be done by ſuch Superiours in theſe Caſes? unleſs this: Either that in the things of God, they be very tender, and enjoyn no ſuch things, as any conſiderable Number of their Inferiours thus Judge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, (at leaſt, if they Judge them not by God Commanded to be done, or to be avoided,) Or if they Judge it expedient to Command ſome other things for <hi>Splendor,</hi> or (as they Judge) <hi>Decency</hi> which the Inſeriours cannot Judge Lawful; <hi>Indulge them,</hi> who ſo cannot Judge of them, as themſelves do, but verily believing them, from Arguments which appear to them probable, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful</hi> for them to do; which is our preſent Caſe. For whiles the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in ſuch things as theſe, inſiſteth upon his Authority, he unavoidably for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them to <hi>ſin againſt God,</hi> who ſo Judge them unlawful, yet through ſome <hi>Fear,</hi> or out of ſome <hi>Temptation</hi> of <hi>want,</hi> or the like, will adventure to do them. Now, no Soul can Juſtifie it ſelf before God, in Commanding ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to do what he knows would <hi>be ſin to him,</hi> unleſs it would alſo be <hi>ſin in him,</hi> not to Command or force him. And for others who dare Act, he <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them to ſuffer,</hi> in which Caſe, becauſe (their Conſciences ſo Judging of the things) they ſhould <hi>ſin</hi> in doing of them, they muſt <hi>ſuffer</hi> to <hi>avoid
ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> which we are ſure is, (in one ſence at leaſt) <hi>to ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake;</hi> and for what they Judge (to uſe Dr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s phraſe) <hi>the Exerciſe of the True Religion;</hi> and all Sober Perſons will ſo judge in the firſt ſence: and whether it be ſo or no, <hi>The great day of the Lord muſt Evidence.</hi> Both which certainly are Rocks, which all Superiours ought to avoid, and all Wiſe <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> and <hi>Maſters Mates,</hi> in the great Ships of Kingdoms, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths will avoid, though ſome leſs adviſed <hi>Boat-ſwains, paſſionate Chaplains,</hi> or <hi>ignorant Mariners</hi> in thoſe Ships, may clamour, to take the Advantage of the Wind of <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Revenge,</hi> which blows (they think) in theſe Caſes fair for the Advantage of their private Lucre, but muſt certainly drive them, either upon this <hi>Seylla,</hi> or that <hi>Charibdis.</hi> Every conſiderate Superiour will Judge the price of Souls purchaſed with the Blood of him who was the Son of God, at another rate. Indeed if the Superiour judgeth the things which he Commandeth, in their own Nature neceſſary, and what it is the Will of God (antecedaneous to his Command) that all Men ſhould do, whether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they be ſo or no. He is alſo tyed to <hi>the Peace of his own Conſcience;</hi> he is Gods <hi>Vice-gerent,</hi> he muſt Command, and inforce them; and the doing of what is plain to him, to be the great Creators Will, in his place, muſt be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended before the danger of any Creatures Souls; and this alone (where
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:109403:48"/>the Superiours Conſcience is fixed in an Error) neceſſarily cauſeth a
<hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 17. This appeareth to us ſo clear, both from Scripture, and the Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judgment of all <hi>Proteſtant Divines,</hi> for <hi>a Mans not Acting contrary to the Opinion of his own Conſcience;</hi> that we cannot be ſo Charitable, but we muſt think, that thoſe Divines who indeed are Proteſtants, and are for the <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding theſe impoſitions,</hi> and againſt any <hi>Indulgence</hi> to thoſe that <hi>diſſent</hi> becauſe of them, and are Authors to Magiſtrates, to inforce the things by Penalties; are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Condemned by their own Conſciences. For they cannot but know, that the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> thus <hi>Opining,</hi> muſt ſin, ſhould they do the things: and if they <hi>Suffer,</hi> they muſt <hi>Suffer</hi> that they might <hi>avoid ſinning.</hi> And for the Interpretation of that, <q>What it is for a Superiour, not contrained in his own Conſcience from the expreſs revealed Will of God, to make his Inferiours Suffer, becauſe they will not do what they cannot do, without running the hazard of their Souls by wilful ſinning: <hi>We ſhall onely ſay,</hi> Let the Interpretation be to them that hate our King, <hi>and to</hi> the Enemies of all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility or Gentry.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. To Conclude then, this we Judge enough to demonſtrate the exceeding <hi>Reaſonableneſs,</hi> and <hi>great Religion</hi> of a <hi>Gracious Liberty;</hi> to which His moſt Sacred Majeſty hath Declared his Willingneſs, and the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of which</hi> hath once and again been under the <hi>Deliberation of the High and Honourable Aſſembly of Parliament:</hi> as to thoſe, whoſe Suffering by it is obviated, becauſe they cannot do what they Charitably believe their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours would not have willed them to do, had they not Judged them in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Lawful; But yet themſelves will not ſay are neceſſary (otherwiſe than as they are pleaded to be ſo made by their Command) but they who are their Inferiours, do <hi>bonâ fide</hi> and <hi>ex animo,</hi> Judge them Unlawful; and that from Arguments, which they will not call <hi>neceſſary, indubitable,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative</hi> (for they confeſs themſelves not Infallible) but which appear to them very highly probable, ſuch as they cannot Anſwer, nor find Anſwered by others, ſo as to give them any Satisfaction.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:109403:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
